<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Art of assassinating kings taught Lewis XIV and James II by the Jesuites : wherein is discovered the secret of the last conspiracy form'd at Versailles in Sep. 1695, against the life of William III, King of Great Britain, and discover'd at White-Hall, Feb. 1695/6.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25894</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3785</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24187</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08043708</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08043708</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40768</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25894)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40768)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1221:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Art of assassinating kings taught Lewis XIV and James II by the Jesuites : wherein is discovered the secret of the last conspiracy form'd at Versailles in Sep. 1695, against the life of William III, King of Great Britain, and discover'd at White-Hall, Feb. 1695/6.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>131 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by E. Whitlock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Done out of French."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Regicides.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40768:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40768:1"/>
            <p>The ART of <hi>Aſſaſſinating</hi> KINGS, TAUGHT <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. &amp; <hi>James</hi> II. By the JESUITES. Wherein is Diſcovered, The Secret of the laſt Conſpiracy, form'd at <hi>Verſailles</hi> in <hi>Sep.</hi> 1695. againſt the Life of <hi>William</hi> III. King of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> And diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd at <hi>White-Hall, Feb.</hi> 1695/6.</p>
            <p>Done out of <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, and ſold by <hi>E. Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40768:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40768:2"/>
            <head>The ART of <hi>Aſſaſſinating</hi> KINGS.</head>
            <p>MOſt SERENE PRINCES, at this Day in Confederacy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>France.</hi> Here is a Facinorous Attempt, which ought to make all the Crowned Heads of <hi>Europe</hi> tremble. 'Tis a Conſpiracy laid to Aſſaſſinate the Sacred Perſon of the KING of Great <hi>BRITAIN.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40768:3"/> This Affair excites your ſelves to be careful in Good Earneſt, of your own Preſervation, no leſs than it concerns that Renowned Prince himſelf, to be watchful of his own Safety.</p>
            <p>The means which the moſt Chriſtian King, and K. <hi>James</hi> made uſe of, were almoſt Infallible; in ſo much, that only God alone was able to divert and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoint 'em. Witneſs the Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings own Words: <hi>'Tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>but this Deſign muſt prove ſucceſsful, unleſs God and the Winds prevent it.</hi> In the mean time, there is nothing more dear to Us in this World then Life; and the Lives of Princes are ſo pretious, that often up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Sacred Lives, depend the Greateſt Revolutions, the Ruine of their Subjects, and the Deſolation of their Dominions.</p>
            <p>When an unforeſeen Misfortune, a violent Diſeaſe, or ſudden Death, may have ſnatch'd from the World thoſe Princes, who were the Glory of their Age, and the Love of the People, there nothing remains behind for Us, but Tears and Lamentations. This is all the Duty we can pay 'em; tho' could we by our Blood redeem 'em from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40768:3"/> Grave, there is no good Subject who would not bleed to the laſt Drop. We have had a Glorious Example of this, in the late loſs which we ſuſtain'd of the Queen of Great <hi>Britain.</hi> That Princeſs was ſnatch'd from Us in the Flower of her Age: However, we have this to comfort our ſelves, that we are all mortal. The Misfortune was inevitable; and it was a natural Diſeaſe that raviſh'd her from us.</p>
            <p>But what a dreadful thing it is, when Swords and Poyſon are made uſe of, to hurry out of the world Great Princes, ſignally eminent for their Piety, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd of their Subjects, dear to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtian Princes, and the chief Hero's of the Age? What a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing, I ſay, it is, when the Authors of ſuch a deteſtable Deſign, are Crowned Heads? They who in After-Ages ſhall come to read the Lives of theſe two Wretched Princes, will they not bluſh d'ye think? Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Exemplars, that ſacrifice the Glory of their Reigns, the Title of Moſt Chriſtian, and all that is account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt Sacred, Moſt Auguſt in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and in Humane Society, to the deceitful Fantom of their Ambition.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:40768:4"/>
            <p>But, moſt Serene Princes, at this day Confederated together for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Safety, What Precautions ought you not to take, to ſecure your ſelves againſt the Contrivances of ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators as theſe. For I muſt repeat it once more, Your Lives are no leſs in Danger, then the Life of Your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate King <hi>WILLIAM.</hi> 'Tis your Alliance with this Great Prince, of which your Enemies are jealous, that gave Birth to this deteſtable Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that has been ſo lately diſcover'd. 'Tis an Attempt that concerns yee eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one in particular; for had the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators accompliſh'd their Deſign, what Miſchiefs, what Calamities, had You not had juſt reaſon to have been apprehenſive of in reference to your ſelves?</p>
            <p>All <hi>Europe</hi> is ſufficiently acquainted with the Ways and Methods which the Tyrannic Politicks of <hi>France</hi> make uſe of, and which they have made uſe of for theſe Eight Years of declar'd War together, to accompliſh their Ends; that is to ſay, the Enſlaving of all the Soveraign Princes of <hi>Europe.</hi> There has not been a Year ſince the Death of <hi>Mazarine,</hi> that has not produc'd a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40768:4"/> Monſter: So that the Reign of the Moſt Chriſtian King has been a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Series of Enormous Attempts and Conſpiracies.</p>
            <p>If this Monarch have made ſuch a Noiſe in the World; if he is become the Terrour of his Enemies, 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, that beſides his great Power which diſtinguiſhes him from other Chriſtian Princes, he has always had recourſe to Treachery, as his laſt Refuge in all the moſt deſperate Streſſes of his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; ſo that if we have ſeen him gain ſurprizing Conqueſts in the midſt of <hi>Winter,</hi> take ſtrong Towns in the face of Armies looking on, win Battels, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack the Confederates in Poſts almoſt impenetrable, and deceive the Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy of our Generals, they have only been the Effects of Treachery, and the fatal Conſequences of our Remiſsneſs.</p>
            <p>If War be to be carry'd on by Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery and Infidelity, there's no rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon any thing. Where is the Glory of Arms, that Glory almoſt as ancient as the World, which after Death, reſtor'd to a new Life thoſe Hero's and great Captains, who are propos'd to us for the Models of all our Enterprizes, ſuch as <hi>Caeſars, Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40768:5"/> Pompeys, Charles</hi> the Great's, <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth's, and other Renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſonages tranſmitted to us by Antiquity?</p>
            <p>Nor will I deny, but that this Age affords ſome Patterns like thoſe Hero's of former times, but I cannot ſay thoſe Vertues are to be found in one Great King, a Moſt Chriſtian King, an Eldeſt Son of the Church. This is an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which ought to make all <hi>French</hi> Men bluſh. But you will ſay, that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are not to be reſponſible for the Miſcarriages of their Prince. 'Tis a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Stain, I grant it; I am aſham'd to ſay it: The Noble Blood of the <hi>Bourbons,</hi> that has glitter'd in ſo many preceding Reigns, is now ſully'd with ſo many foul Attempts, that the very thought of it ſtrikes a Horror into all People of Worth.</p>
            <p>I cannot here forbear to ſet down the lovely Idea, which <hi>Pagan</hi> Authors had of True Royalty, which ought to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Moſt Chriſtian King with Shame and Confuſion. <hi>He is truly a King who is truly juſt. He is truly juſt, who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns himſelf according to the Laws. There is no Juſtice that can ſubſiſt without Law. Let him that aſcends the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40768:5"/> Throne be pure, and environ'd with the bright ſhining Rays of Juſtice,</hi> ſays <hi>Ecphantas</hi> the Philoſopher. True Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ordains, that the Crimes of High Treaſon, and all Attempts of wicked Men, ſhould be puniſh'd with utmoſt Rigour; and it may be ſaid, That this is one of the Nobleſt Characters of Royalty. And yet at this day we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Two Princes authorizing a Crew of Aſſaſſines and Murderers, to embrue their Impious Hands; if it had been poſſible, in the Blood of a Great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.</p>
            <p>After a Blow of this Importance, we may freely ſay, That the moſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Confederates, may juſtly make the moſt Chriſtian King the ſame An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which <hi>Alexander</hi> gave <hi>Darius,</hi> when deſpairing to overcome the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonian</hi> by Arms, he would fain have had him Aſſaſſinated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> gave him to underſtand, <hi>That he would no longer make War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as againſt a Prince, but as a Parricide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will any body ſay, that if the moſt Chriſtian King continues theſe Projects, it will of neceſſity behove the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates to make uſe of the ſame means?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40768:6"/> Would they have Villany puniſh'd by Villany? Or that if great Sums of Money muſt be given to rid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their Enemies, and put an end to the War all at once, by deſtroying the Head of the Party by Aſſaſſination; will any body deny but that <hi>France</hi> will ſooner want Money then the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſederates, or at leaſt that the Princes of the League are not rich enough to conſtrain the moſt Chriſtian King to ſtand upon his Guard in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular? He can lay claim to no Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, nor to being Invulnerable, no more then his Predeceſſors <hi>Henry</hi> III. or <hi>Henry</hi> IV.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, theſe deteſtable Ways of Deſtroying an Enemy, by a violent and haſten'd Death, by Poyſon or Dagger, are open to the Confederates as well as for the moſt Chriſtian King. But God forbid that ever any one of the moſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Confederates ſhould ever have ſo black a Thought. They have ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy'd another ſort of Morality in the School of Vertue: Their Piety and the Niceneſs of their Conſciences ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor and deteſt thoſe Principles, which deduc'd their Original from Hell, and and which were never preach'd in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40768:6"/> 
               <hi>France</hi> but by the JESUITES, nor ſo much as taught ambitious Princes by <hi>Matchiavel</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>We are thoroughly convinc'd, that <hi>France</hi> ſufficiently ingenious to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the unlucky untucky Blows which ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives from Fortune, will endeavour to eſcape the Ignominy which this deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Enterprize will ſix upon her, by a ſtudy'd Apology compos'd by ſome one of her moſt able and dextrous Miniſters. Methinks I hear already the Count <hi>d' Avaux</hi> in one of the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern</hi> Courts, and M. <hi>Amelot</hi> among the <hi>Switzers,</hi> loudly proteſting, that the moſt Chriſtian King their Maſter, had no hand in this Attempt, but that it was form'd by the JACOBITES in <hi>England,</hi> without ever being commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to his knowledge.</p>
            <p>But this has been the Language of that Prince in all the preceding Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies; witneſs that of <hi>Granval.</hi> The Court of <hi>France</hi> laid all the load upon her Miniſters, and threw all the Blame upon the deceas'd Marquis of <hi>Louvois,</hi> and his Son M. <hi>d' Barbeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eux.</hi> All this while, the world knows under what a ſort of awe the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> live; had they made the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40768:7"/> leaſt ſtep without the Kings knowledge, there would have needed no more to have render'd their Fidelity ſuſpected, and to have diſgrac'd'em for ever. The Miniſters of the Court of <hi>France.</hi> are too wary of preſerving their Poſts, to commit ſuch Miſtakes; there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing tranſacted within that Kingdom, with which the King is not acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if the King of <hi>France,</hi> as he gives out in Foreign Courts, had no hand in the late diſcover'd Conſpiracy, Whence came that numerous FLEET, which of a ſudden was Rendezvous'd together in the Ports of <hi>Dunkirk, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, Bologne,</hi> and <hi>Havre de Grace?</hi> Did that Potent Preparation fall from the Clouds? So many Troops drawn down together to the Sea-ſide, were they ſent to Guard the Coaſts of <hi>France,</hi> at a time when the Enemies FLEET was only fitting out, half Mann'd, and not in a probability of putting to Sea till the end of <hi>April?</hi> What did M. <hi>Bouf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers,</hi> and ſo many <hi>French</hi> Generals do at <hi>Dunkirk?</hi> For what reaſon did K. <hi>James</hi> leave St. <hi>Germains?</hi> For what reaſon take his leave ſo ſolemnly of all the Court, and flye to take ſhipping at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40768:7"/> 
               <hi>Callis?</hi> To what end the Prayers of Fourty Hours, and the publication of a <hi>Jubilee?</hi> Will the moſt Chriſtian King ſay, that all this was done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his being made acquainted with it?</p>
            <p>K. <hi>James</hi> having left St. <hi>Germains</hi> the 28th of <hi>February,</hi> came to St. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi>'s, where he perform'd his Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and after he had begg'd of God in his fervent Prayers, to bleſs his Expedition, he ſent for a Publick No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, whom he order'd to draw up an Act for the Sum of 500 Thouſand Livres, which he had borrow'd of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Merchants, for which he gave 'em in Pawn, the Queen his Wives Jewels.</p>
            <p>Beſides this Sum, the moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King Orders Six Millions to be paid him forthwith, and made him a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent over and above of a little Cheſt, containing a Hundred Thouſand <hi>Loui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores</hi> in Specie, to defray his Houſhold Expences. <hi>France</hi> did not ſhew him all theſe Kindneſſes for nothing: She exacted at the ſame time real Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the Careſs'd Prince, that is to ſay, a Contract or Deed acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd before a Publick Notary. by which K. <hi>James</hi> obliges himſelf to pay
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40768:8"/> back to the moſt Chriſtian King, after his Reſtauration, not only the Sum lent him for his Paſſage, but all that <hi>France</hi> had disburs'd for his Support, during his abode in that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian King, I ſay, lends all his Forces to this miſerable Prince, ſpares him his beſt Generals to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his Troops, and ſuffers him to want nothing for the Execution of a Deſign, that was to reſeat him upon hi Throne. And all this acted in the full view of all <hi>Europe;</hi> But the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize miſcarrying, the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King Orders his Miniſters to tell us, That he had no hand in it.</p>
            <p>'Tis not the firſt time that the <hi>Frehch</hi> Monarch has talk'd at this rate. But the Confederates are no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be deluded with Words; not will all the Water in the <hi>Seine,</hi> be able to waſh away a Crime ſo black as this, which has been committed in the ſight of God and all Chriſtendom, by the Aſſaſſination intended to have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated upon the Sacred Perſon of King <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> complotted at <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feilles</hi> the 1ſt. of <hi>October,</hi> in the Year 1695.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40768:8"/>
            <p>Let us conclude then, that the moſt Chriſtian King being the Principal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this deteſtable Attempt, all the ſhame of it rebounds back upon his own Perſon. K. <hi>James</hi> is a feeble and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puiſſant Prince of himſelf. 'Tis true, that he was bred in Slaughter and But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery; his whole Life has been a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Train of Tragical Deaths, Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates and Conſpiracies: Witneſs the innocent Blood which he has ſhed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his abode in <hi>England.</hi> But this Unfortunate Prince, notwithſtanding the depravement of his natural Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and his unbridl'd falſe Zeal for Religion, could have done nothing of himſelf, had not the moſt Chriſtian King ſupported him. You'll ſay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, that <hi>France</hi> is a weary of paying him his Penſions, and that She would be glad to be rid of him. Let it be which way it will, the moſt Chriſtian King is He that is look't upon as the principal Author of this intended Perpetration; an Act which in After-Ages, all good Chriſtian Princes will look upon with Horror, and which now renders him unworthy of the Gorious Title of moſt Chriſtian King.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40768:9"/>
            <p>'Tis a long time that the Council of <hi>France</hi> had been hatching this Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, which ſhe was about to have brought forth, as may eaſily appear, if we reflect upon the Conduct of her Miniſters in Foreign Courts. For when the Popes Nuncio'd redoubl'd their Importunities to perſuade the Catholick Princes to accept of the Propoſals that were made 'em; The Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> openly told 'em, There was no ſuch need for 'em to be ſo haſty; for that the moſt Chriſtian King their Maſter, had a Deſign in hand which would change the Face of Affairs, and force the Confederates to accept of the Offers that had been ſo frequently made 'em, and which they had rejected with ſo much ſcorn.</p>
            <p>This Vaunting was a Riddle not to be expounded by his Holineſs Nouncio's, till Time, that notable <hi>Oedipus,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolded the <hi>Enigma,</hi> to the eternal Shame of the Heads of the Enterprize, and of thoſe that were to have been their Inſtruments. We may alſo add by the way, to the ſhame of the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters, who thus diſcours'd the Popes Nuncio's, who are no better then their Maſter, while they are the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40768:9"/> Eccho's of an Action that will load 'em with eternal Infamy. They boaſt to be the Miniſters of their Princes Fury, at the Expence of their Honour and their Conſciences, which they ought to prize above all things in the World. They ought to call to mind the inſinite Injury they do their Nation, and the foul Stains of Infamy with which they ſully it, and which will not be waſh'd off in ſeveral Reigns after This.</p>
            <p>If we conſider farther, what paſſed at the Taking of <hi>Namure,</hi> at what time the Perſon of Marſhal <hi>Boufflers</hi> was ſeiz'd; all the World knows, the Marſhal made loud Complaints, and haughtily exclaim'd againſt the Injury done him, adding, <hi>That his Maſter would Revenge the Injuſtice that had been offer'd him upon the Perſon of the</hi> PRINCE, <hi>who had ſo caus'd him to be ſtopt.</hi> M. <hi>Boufflers</hi> had been made Privy to the Conſpiracy, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'twas no wonder thoſe Words of Paſſion dropt from him. Wherefore the moſt Chriſtian King judg'd him ſo neceſſary for this great Expedition, that he vouchſaf'd to honour him forthwith with a Brevet for a Duke and Peer of <hi>France;</hi> and conſented to all things
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40768:10"/> that the Confederates demanded, to obtain his ſpeedy Liberty.</p>
            <p>Till now, we flatter'd our ſelves, that <hi>France</hi> would no longer have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to all thoſe Treacheries, of which She made ſo good a uſe, while M. <hi>Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> commanded her Arms. But M. <hi>Boufflers</hi> ſeems to be ſprung up from the Aſhes of that Famous Captain, tho' according to all Appearances, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple will not prove much better then his Maſter.</p>
            <p>However. M. <hi>Boufflers,</hi> with his good leave, does a great Injury to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and 'tis a bad Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to have had a ſhare in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Aſſaſſination, of a Prince that heap'd ſo many Favours and Civilities upon him during his Detention. There is no need of going to ſeek him out in <hi>England.</hi> King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> does not hide himſelf, as all the World knows. He is none of thoſe timerous Princes that ſhun Danger. He appears every Campagne in <hi>Flanders,</hi> at the Head of his Armies. And if the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King, or his Generals, deſire an end of the War, and to obtain that Peace which they ſo much thirſt after, He is always ready to anſwer their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40768:10"/> Expectations, with his Sword in his Hand. They might alſo, out of a Principle of Honour, make him that fair Challenge, which the Prince E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector, formerly ſent to M. <hi>Turenne;</hi> that is to ſay, by the Propoſal of a ſingle Combat, in order to determine the Differences that have inflam'd this War by the point of the Sword, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the King of <hi>France</hi> himſelf would be one of the Champions in Perſon.</p>
            <p>But that is not the thing which the King of <hi>France</hi> ſeeks after: He has been accuſtom'd to vanquiſh without Danger; and indeed, 'tis the way to live long. In a word, Were King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> leſs Brave, and leſs Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous then he is, the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King, and K. <hi>James,</hi> would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make thoſe attempts upon his Perſon which they do.</p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian King, ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace, has been accuſtom'd to make his Progreſſes with a kind of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidneſs; becauſe he was aſſur'd of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> through the Care which he took to cultivate the Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the laſt Kings, as all <hi>Europe</hi> well knows. 'Twas under the ſhelter
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40768:11"/> of thoſe Careleſs and voluptuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reigns, that he rear'd this Monſter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Grandeur, which makes him ſo formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable to his Neighbours, ſo fear'd by his Subjects, and ſo daring in all his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes to mix Heaven and Earth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>But thoſe Reigns are paſt; the Cards are all mix'd; and the laſt Revolution which advanc'd King <hi>William</hi> to the Throne, was the moſt terrible Blow that ever was given to <hi>France;</hi> becauſe that Prince has been all along his irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable Enemy, the only Prince in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> who has croſs'd his ambitious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, who has always diſputed the Ground with him, and who, like ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Joſhua,</hi> has ſtopp'd the Sun in his rapid Courſe.</p>
            <p>So that the moſt Chriſtian King find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Puiſſance of King <hi>William</hi> as Head of the League, would prove an invincible Obſtacle to his Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes, thought it convenient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Principles of his Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannick Politicks, to rid himſelf of this Prince by one means or other For proof of which, it has been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, that in all the Battels that have hitherto been fought, the <hi>French</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40768:11"/> Generals have been very careful to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ick out a good Number of the Guards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the King's Houſhold, to make way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrough the Throng, in Order to Kill King <hi>William.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>de Luxemburgh</hi> did all that lay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his power, to ſatisfie the King his Maſter in this Particular; and M. <hi>de Boufflers,</hi> no leſs zealous then his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor, makes no ſcruple to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the Head of a Crew of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, to ſecond the Aſſaſſination of this Noble Prince. At the Battel of the <hi>Boyn,</hi> the Guards who kill'd M. <hi>de Scomberg,</hi> had Orders to find out the King; but God preſerv'd him, and brought him ſafe out of the Snares which <hi>France</hi> and K. <hi>James</hi> had laid for him. After ſo many Proofs of the King of <hi>France</hi>'s extraordinary care to deſtroy this Prince, there is no queſtion to be made, but that he was the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> of this laſt Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy.</p>
            <p>There needs no more then this bold Stroke, to embelliſh the Hiſtory of this Monarch, which the beſt Pens of <hi>France</hi> have been labouring for ſo many Years to ſet out. This will be a moſt gay and flouriſhing Flower in his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40768:12"/> Crown; a Monument, then which he cannot conſecrate a more auguſt to Poſterity. It may be ſaid, that by this Inglorious Action, the Mighty Monarch leaves a Glorious Example for the <hi>Dauphin</hi> to imitate, if his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Father do not out-live him a or at leaſt for his Children to take a Pattern by, who are young enough to ſtudy Virtue under ſo Great a Maſter. After ſuch an Attempt as this, the Moſt Chriſtian King has reaſon to reſt himſelf from his Illuſtrious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and dye well ſatisfied. He has Reign'd a Great Monarch, a Great Politician, always happy and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; if he now miſs'd his Blow, he muſt look upon it, that only Heaven put by the Fatal Stroak, which he ſo fairly offer'd.</p>
            <p>But as for You, Monſieur <hi>Dauphin,</hi> 'tis hop'd that your Inclinations will not lead you to follow this Great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar: We are ſenſible that you, like the deceaſed Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> abhor ſuch Treacherous Actions as theſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of a great Hero, more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially a Chriſtian Prince, one day de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to wear one of the moſt Auguſt Crowns in Chriſtendom.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40768:12"/>
            <p>All <hi>Europe</hi> looks upon You, as one that will reſtore that Peace and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility which your Father's unjuſt Claims have baniſh'd from among the Chriſtian Princes. If it be the Pleaſure of Heaven that ever you come to the Crown, we moſt juſtly flatter our ſelves, that <hi>France</hi> was never ſo happy as it will be then. Your Subjects will be deliver'd from the Burthens of a thouſand Impoſts; Trade will be reſtor'd; Arts and Sciences will flouriſh; the Nobility of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will reaſſume their Ancient Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor; the Parliaments, and Sovereign Courts will again enjoy that Authority of which they have been deſpoil'd; the Neighbouring Princes will have a plenary Confidence in your Royal Word; your Treaties will be invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable; and you will be lookt upon in all the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> as a Prince that treads in the Steps of your Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Anceſtors, and not purſue the Vices of two Monarchs, that ſtrike a Horror of their Actions into the Hearts of all the Chriſtian Princes.</p>
            <p>Call to mind, Sir, the Precepts of the Wiſe <hi>Plato, That the Laws have a Power over Kings, as well as Subjects.</hi> So long as you take ſuch Principles for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40768:13"/> the Rule of your Actions, you will be the Love of your Subjects, the Glory of your Age, and the Greateſt King in the World.</p>
            <p>All <hi>Europe,</hi> Sir, conjures you to inculcate theſe Noble Leſſons into the young Princes your Sons, who are one day to ſucceed you; 'tis time to do it, but more eſpecially to infuſe into their tender years an Averſion and Abhorrency of the Deteſtable Principles of their Grandfather, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by all good men: Inſtil into them this noble Thought of <hi>Aristotle, He whom the People will not admit for King, is a Tyrant:</hi> ſo long as they have the Love of the People, they will be worthy to wear a Crown. This is that which is the greateſt Glory of that Prince, whom the Moſt Chriſtian King your Father, and his Allie King <hi>James</hi> would have Aſſaſſinated: he is paſſionately belov'd of his Subjects, and conſequently worthy to be their King. This Love it is, which aſſures him of their Fidelity, which eſtabliſhes his Throne, and renders it immoveable; and which is the Reaſon that his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects will ſpend the laſt drop of their Blood for the Preſervation of his Sacred Perſon.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40768:13"/>
            <p>The want of this Love, ſo neceſſary for Princes that will Govern according to Law, was the cauſe of King <hi>James</hi>'s Misfortunes, and that which renders him the moſt miſerable of Monarchs. But would to Heaven that this were the only Stain that renders him odious; all the Chriſtian Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> would then have no reaſon to upbraid him with the moſt deteſtable of all Crimes, the meditated Aſſaſſination of King <hi>William.</hi> But let us return to the moſt Chriſtian King.</p>
            <p>If we conſider what happen'd upon the Birth of that Prince, we ſhall meet with nothing but what is ſurprizing. All <hi>France</hi> before that, was in great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and all in Tears beſought of God an Heir to the Crown. After two and twenty Years of Barrenneſs, the Queen-Mother conceiv'd; and ſhe brough forth a Succeſſor to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. But what Succeſſor? A Prince that came into the World with Two Teeth. A ſtrange Prodigy! and the moſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing that has happen'd in our days. When the Soothſayers of <hi>Italy</hi> were conſulted by Expreſſes, which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed M. <hi>de Colbert</hi> ſent thither, they anſwer'd, That the Prince newly born,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40768:14"/> with Two Teeth, ſhould with One of his Teeth tear his Subjects, with the Other, the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p>In a word, never was Horoſcope bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fulfill'd. The Commencements of his Reign are full of Prodigies, and hitherto the End has been no leſs ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing. Hardly was he arriv'd at the Age of Majority, but he began with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the greateſt part of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: He deſpoils the Parliaments and Soveraign Courts of all they had which was moſt Auguſt, the Supream Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. He humbled the Nobility of his Kingdom; impoveriſh'd his Subjects by an infinite number of new Taxes: He raiſes great Armies to keep 'em un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Submiſſion and Reſpect: He forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the greateſt part of the Strong Holds in his Kingdom, to enſlave the whole, and ſerve as Ramparts to his Ambition. He lets looſe his Fury a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> and he alone commits more Attentats againſt the Soveraign Pontiffs, then all his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors together had ever done.</p>
            <p>After theſe happy Beginnings, he ſtudies <hi>Machiavel,</hi> and got him ſo well by Heart, that his whole Reign was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40768:14"/> but a Tiſſue of that Author's Precepts. He obſerves 'em to the moſt minute Maxims; and by the help of <hi>Mazarin,</hi> he became ſo Great a Maſter in the Art of Reigning, that the Bounds of <hi>France</hi> could no longer contain him. There is not any Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> that has not been a Victim to his Ambition. If he makes Alliances, 'tis only to aggran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize himſelf by Violation of his Oaths: If he declares War, 'tis unjuſt, becauſe his only Aim is the Invaſion of his Neighbour's Dominions: If he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes a Peace, 'tis only to break it to morrow, and that he may have new Pretences to recommence the War.</p>
            <p>In a word, there is no Sovereign Prince, no Elector in the Empire, no Republick in <hi>Europe,</hi> that is not ſenſible of the Effects of his cruel Domination. The preſent War has thrown its diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Firebrands into all the Corners of the World. All Chriſtendom enjoy'd a profound Peace, at what time the moſt Chriſtian King ſent Armies of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries, with lighted Flambeaux in their hands, to Fire the moſt Noble Cities of <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This diſmal Conflagration, after it had reduced the <hi>Palatinate</hi> into Aſhes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40768:15"/> was extended by the hands of M. <hi>de Boufflers</hi> all along the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle,</hi> and thence through all <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Brabant;</hi> and ſo over-running, like a Mad-man and a Fury, all the open Country he burnt all before him, ſparing neither Churches nor Monaſteries.</p>
            <p>All theſe Cruelties were acted in view of all the Princes of <hi>Europe;</hi> but there was none but King <hi>William,</hi> who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied himſelf in earneſt to ſtop the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer of <hi>France.</hi> The People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> call'd this Great Prince to their Succour, becauſe the moſt Chriſtian King Reign'd no leſs in the Three Kingdoms of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> then in <hi>France,</hi> by virtue of the Cruelties which King <hi>James,</hi> his Confederate, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd therein. King <hi>William</hi> paſſes the Sea, ſupported by the hands of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; he is received with all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours immaginable by the Nobility of the Kingdom, and by the People. The Crown is preſented to him, and he is deſired to accept it; which he does, after <hi>Long Importunities,</hi> becauſe the preſent Condition of the Affairs of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> and the Safety of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weal engag'd him to it.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40768:15"/>
            <p>By that means he gave a deadly Blow to <hi>France,</hi> ſo much the rather, becauſe ſhe little dreamt of ſuch a Revolution. Thereupon after that, the moſt Chriſtian King minds nothing but Revenge. The Hatred which he had all along for that Prince, could no longer be kept within bounds; it muſt break forth, and fling about its fiery Indignation. And from that day forward his ſecret Council met, with Orders to ſeek out ſome way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this Prince, as the only Perſon able to put a ſtop to his Great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. So that ſince his coming to the Crown, we may reckon up near 8 Conſpiracies; only this laſt exceeded all the reſt. The Conſpirators in this, never go about to conceal themſelves: They walk barefac'd at Noon-day, and rely upon the Death of King <hi>William,</hi> as upon a thing that cannot fail 'em. After this, I leave the World to judge, how far the Fury and Reſentment of a Prince will go, who has ſworn the Death of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</p>
            <p>I cannot here forbear to recite the words of <hi>Saluſt,</hi> when he ſpeaks of the Care that Princes ought to take of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40768:16"/> the Honour of their Dominions, of which they ought to be as jealous as of their own Crowns. <hi>The Duty of Kings,</hi> ſays he, <hi>conſiſts in preſerving the Liberty and Honour of a Kingdom.</hi> But the moſt Chriſtian King ne're troubles himſelf for the Honour of <hi>France:</hi> He Sacrifices it with a good will, provided his Deſigns do but ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. Where is that Liberty, I would fain know, which his Subjects enjoy'd in the Reigns of his Predeceſſors? Are they not all at preſent Slaves within the Kingdom? Where is the Honour of the Kingdom? Is it acquir'd by Oppreſſion, Cruelty and Tyranny? And when it is acquir'd, is it preſerv'd by the Aſſaſſination of Great Princes, for whom they have a mortal Hatred?</p>
            <p>If this be true, I muſt acknowledge the Antients to have been very great Cheats, for having made us ſuch a Deſcription of the Honour of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſo far different from that which <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Grand</hi> gives us the preſent Pattern of. This Prince pretends to be the greateſt Model of Perfection this day in the World. But with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to him, the Courſe he takes, is not the way to attain to the Glory
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40768:16"/> of thoſe Great Hero's, of which Pagan Antiquity has left us ſuch Noble Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplars.</p>
            <p>After theſe Preliminaries, let us come to the Particulars of matter of Fact, and conſider all the Circumſtances that accompany'd this Conſpiracy, ſo lately diſcover'd: After that, we ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Doctrine of the JESUITES, which teaches the Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings, and which they have taught the Authors of the preſent Conſpiracy.</p>
            <p>God by his Providence, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual care which he takes for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Majeſty King <hi>WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM,</hi> has ſo order'd it, that ſeveral of the Conſpirators, have diſcover'd, of themſelves, the following Conſpiracy the particulars whereof are Theſe.</p>
            <p>About the end of the month of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> in the Year 1695. the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King, being at <hi>Verſailles</hi> in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conference with K. <hi>James,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Events of the preceding Campagne, the moſt Chriſtian King out of a peculiar confidence in him, told him, <q rend="inline">That he ſaw no other way in the world to attain a ſpeedy Peace,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40768:17"/> then by labouring his Reſtoration to the Throne. That all the Care which he had hitherto taken to wage War with his Enemies, together with the immenſe Expences he had been at to ſupport it, had as yet produc'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing effectual: Nevertheleſs, that God had ſo ſufficiently proſper'd his Arms, by the Advantages he had won, till the Death of Marſhal <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburgh,</hi> that he had no reaſon to complain. But that which ſtill trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him, and imprinted in his Mind but ill Preſages of the Future, was the preſent Union between the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> which was ſo far from abating, that it grew ſtronger and ſtronger: That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of that Prince, and the Forces which the Parliament had granted him, would be fatal to the Peace, and the Common Intereſts, unleſs ſome ſudden Courſe were taken.</q>
            </p>
            <p>K. <hi>James</hi> made Anſwer to the moſt Chriſtian King, <q rend="inline">That all that he had ſaid was true; that he ſaw but too well, and with a deep Sorrow, the Proſperity and growing Grandeur of his Enemy; That 'twas only his fault, for that he himſelf was ready at that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40768:17"/> very inſtant, to attempt his Return into <hi>England,</hi> if his Majeſty thought it convenient: Nevertheleſs, that he was aſham'd to have ſo often abus'd his Kindneſſes, and that he was afraid his Evil Stars that follow'd him where e're he went, would fruſtrate the juſteſt Enterprize that he ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake; That both He and the Queen his Wife, beſought Almighty God in their moſt ſervent Prayers, to bleſs the Arms of his Majeſty, their Protector and Reſtorer, in whom; next to God, they plac'd all their Hopes and Confidence.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this the moſt Chriſtian King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, <q rend="inline">That it had not been his Fault hitherto, that their Prayers had not been heard: but that it was not yet too late, and that it behov'd him to lay hold of the ſavourable opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that God had put into his hands, to give their Enemy ſuch a Blow, as would prove fatal to him. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, that it became him to truſt in God, and to arm himſelf with Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution for the execution of the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize.</q>
            </p>
            <p>K. <hi>James</hi> made Anſwer, <q rend="inline">That he underſtood what his Majeſty meant;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40768:18"/> ſo that if no more were requir'd but the forming a new Plot, he had Men anow at command, provided his Majeſty would lay out Money ſufficient for the carrying on ſo great an Enterprize.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian King reply'd, <q rend="inline">That all the Forces in the Kingdom were at his Service, and that he ſhould deſire no other Reward, then the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of having contributed to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After this firſt Overture, the two Kings agreed upon a day to make choice of the Conſpirators; which day being the 5th. of <hi>September</hi> 1695. was no ſooner come, but the Accomplices were call'd one after another to a private Audience given 'em by K. <hi>James</hi> at St. <hi>Germains;</hi> which at firſt was only to ſound 'em, and aſſure himſelf of their Fidelity.</p>
            <p>At length K. <hi>James</hi> having made choice of about ſeven and forty Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, preſented 'em to the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King, who aſſur'd 'em of his Royal Protection, and of the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Fortunes, if the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſucceeded: After which they were diſmiſſed till further Order.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:40768:18"/>
            <p>At firſt, there were none but the two Kings, and Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> who were Privy to the Secret. For the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King thought it convenient, that when the Buſineſs was drawn into Form, that the Intrigue and Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, ſhould be left to Father <hi>La Chaiſe:</hi> To which K. <hi>James</hi> conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. So that the Conſpirators had Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to repair to him, two and two at a time, for fear of making too much Noiſe, to confer with that Seraphic Prieſt about the Time, Place and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, of putting the Deſign in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>There were ſome of the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors who offer'd their Majeſties to go into <hi>Flanders,</hi> and do the Buſineſs at the time that King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> quitted the Army: But the moſt Chriſtan King did not think that the beſt way, <q rend="inline">becauſe added he, he had not been well ſatisfyed with <hi>Grandvall</hi>'s Conduct, whoſe Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize had miſcarry'd for want of Management, notwithſtanding that the deceaſed Marquiſs of <hi>Louvois,</hi> had taken care to manage it with all the Circumſpection imaginable.</q> K. <hi>James</hi> was of the ſame Opinion, and that the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40768:19"/> Buſineſs might be done with leſs dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger and more eaſe in <hi>England,</hi> becauſe the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had very ſlender Guards there about his Perſon, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when he went a Hunting; whereas in <hi>Flanders</hi> he was always ſurrounded with his Army.</p>
            <p>After ſeveral Conferences, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, That ſome of the Conſpirators ſhould croſs the Sea before-hand, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to confer with ſeveral other JA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COBITES, from whom K. <hi>James</hi> had had particular Letters, aſſuring him of their inviolable Devotion and Readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſacrifice their Blood for his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration.</p>
            <p>All theſe meaſures being taken at the Court of <hi>France,</hi> as may be collected from the Mouths of the Conſpirators themſelves in their Examinations, they fell to work. To which purpoſe, the greateſt part of the Conſpirators that were in <hi>France,</hi> dropt one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into <hi>England,</hi> in ſeveral Privateers, who ſet 'em aſhore upon the Coaſts of <hi>England,</hi> and repair'd to <hi>London.</hi> Where they lay Skulking <hi>Incognito,</hi> to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en their Party againſt the time of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, which was to be accompliſhed about the end of <hi>February</hi> in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:40768:19"/>
            <p>The 25th. of <hi>February</hi> 169<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. which was a <hi>Saturday,</hi> the Conſpirators to the number of Sixty, had reſolv'd to poſt themſelves in ſuch a Place, through which the King was to paſs, in going to <hi>Richmond</hi> to divertize himſelf accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Cuſtom; and to attacque him either in his Coach, or as he was a Hunting: and after they had put the Guards to the Sword, Ten or Twelve were to have made themſelves Maſters of the Kings Coach, and to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht him either with a Dagger or a Blunderbuſs, as they ſaw occaſion.</p>
            <p>But failing that Day, the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors put off the Execution of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Deſign till <hi>Saturday</hi> following. That Day the King's Coach ſtood rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the Guards ſate mounted, and the Proviſion Wagons were gone before: Which being diſcern'd by two of the Conſpirators Spies, who made no doubt but that his Majeſty would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Guards, they haſten'd with all ſpeed to the Rendezvous to give the Traytors information. But his Majeſty thought fit to ſtay that Day at <hi>Kenſington;</hi> and to the end he might have ſome better Light into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, he ſent away ſome Truſty Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40768:20"/> to view the Countenances and Behaviour of ſuch as they ſhould ſee Loytering upon the Roads, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve where they had poſted themſelves. By this ſecond Diſappointment, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be done that day neither: So that the Aſſaſſines reſolved upon the <hi>Sunday</hi> following, to attacque the King in his Paſſage between the two Gates of <hi>Hide-Park</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi>'s, as he went to <hi>White-Hall</hi> to Chappel.</p>
            <p>Their Deſign was firſt to have kill'd the Coach-Horſes, and by that means to have ſtopt the Paſſage of the Guards that follow'd his Majeſty. But the King ſtirr'd not out that day.</p>
            <p>The Night before, or the ſame day the Treaſon was to have been put in Execution, ſeventeen of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators were ſeiz'd, and the next day ſeveral others were taken, among whom were two Dominicans, three Troopers of the E. of <hi>Oxford</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a Trumpeter; one <hi>Charnock,</hi> who had been Vice-Preſident of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> in King <hi>James</hi>'s time, and for which he turn'd Roman Catholick, and ſeveral others. All which, and many more afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, were to have embrued
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40768:20"/> their Murtherous Hands in his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Blood.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi> (Head of the Party) had like to have been taken. One of his Domeſtic Servants was ſeiz'd, who had Orders if the Deſign ſucceeded, to have kindl'd Fires upon the Sea-ſide near <hi>Dover,</hi> which was to have been a Signal to K. <hi>James</hi> and M. <hi>Boufflers,</hi> who lay expecting the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of this great Enterprize. To which purpoſe, the Havens of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk, Callis</hi> and <hi>Bolougne,</hi> were full of Tranſport Ships, which were to have wafted over a great number of Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers into <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to ſecond the JACO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BITES that were to have taken Arms.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Schmettau</hi> Adjutant, being ſent away into <hi>England,</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Wirtenberg,</hi> put himſelf into a Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boat, which being attacqued by a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateer, M. <hi>Schmettau</hi> hid himſelf under the Netts, ſo that the Privateer finding nothing that was Booty, quitted him: After which, he went to <hi>London,</hi> and inform'd the King of the Motions of the <hi>French</hi> on <hi>Dunkirk</hi>-ſide; and his Report was confirm'd by M. <hi>Montez,</hi> Lieutenant Coll. of the Regiment of <hi>Belcaſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:40768:21"/>
            <p>That which is remarkable is this, That the Conſpirators were engag'd for a certain Sum of Money to have accompliſh'd their Deſign within the ſpace of ſix Weeks, and that before the end of <hi>February,</hi> for fear of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Meaſures which the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King had taken for the ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Campagne; whence it came to paſs, that the Enterprize failing upon <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> it was put off till the <hi>Sunday</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: And if Providence had not ſo order'd it, that a good part of the Conſpirators had not been apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it was to be fear'd they would have ſought all the ways in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>inable to have accompliſh'd their de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>able Treaſon.</p>
            <p>We can never too highly applaud the Care which the Earl of <hi>Porland,</hi> and the reſt of the Lords about the King's Perſon, took to prevent ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible a Blow, that would have prov'd no leſs fatal to all Chriſtendom, then to all his Majeſties good Subjects.</p>
            <p>Upon the 24th. of <hi>February</hi> 1696. the King made a Speech to both Houſes of Parliament, wherein he gave 'em an Account of the Aſſaſſination in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended upon his Royal Perſon, and of the Enemies Preparations for a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Invaſion of the Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:40768:21"/>
            <p>Upon this the Houſe of Commons immediately drew up an Aſſociation, wherein they proteſted, teſtify'd and declared ſincerely and ſolemnly, that his Majeſty King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> now Reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is the true and lawful King of the Realms of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and mutually promiſe &amp; engage to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and Aſſiſt each other, to the utmoſt of their Power, to ſupport and defend his Majeſties Sacred Perſon and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment againſt K. <hi>James,</hi> and all his Adherents. And in caſe his Majeſty ſhould come to a violent and haſty Death (which God avert) they volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily and unanimouſly oblige them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to unite; and aſſociate, and to aſſiſt each other to revenge his Death upon his Enemies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was followed by an <hi>Addreſs</hi> of both Houſes, wherein they congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late his happy Preſervation, and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowledge the particular Care of Divine Providence, and at the ſame time declare their deteſtation and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrency of ſo Infamous and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a Deſign, and humbly beſeech his Majeſty to take a more particular Care of his Sacred Perſon.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:40768:22"/>
            <p>Upon which, His Majeſty iſſu'd out ſeveral Proclamations for apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great number of the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, of whom a great part were ſeiz'd and committed to ſeveral Priſons. All which Acts of State have been ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently publiſh'd at large, that they need not be repeated here.</p>
            <p>After ſo many Authentic Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which ought to cover with ſhame the Authors and Contrivers of ſo Black and Treacherous a Fact, all <hi>Europe</hi> ſtands amaz'd! The Miniſters of the Chriſtian Princes aſſembl'd in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, ſit aſtoniſh'd! All the World ſearches for the Cauſes, that excited the wicked Inclinations of theſe two Princes. But there will be no great difficulty in the diſcovery of 'em, when we conſider that the moſt Chriſtian King has always been a true Jeſuite. For proof of which, we need but read the Hiſtory of his Reign. The Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, the Maxims, the dangerous O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and laſtly whatever that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der teaches, not forgetting the <hi>Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings,</hi> have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt quite throughout the whole Courſe of it. As for K. <hi>James,</hi> he left <hi>England,</hi> a true Jeſuite: He has liv'd
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40768:22"/> in <hi>France,</hi> during his Exile, one of the ſame Order; and within theſe two Months, he has thought ſit to Liſt himſelf alſo in the Order of the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had the moſt Chriſtian King taken upon him to read the Determination of the Faculty of Theology in <hi>Paris,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd to the Parliament upon occaſion of the re-ſettlement of the Jeſuits in <hi>France,</hi> I am perſwaded we ſhould not have ſeen him ſo true a Jeſuit as now we do. Wee ſhall repeat the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it in the ſame Terms, as it is in the Original.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="determination">
               <body>
                  <p>In the Year 1554. and upon the Firſt Day of <hi>December,</hi> the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Faculty of <hi>Theology</hi> in <hi>Pars,</hi> after the Maſs of the Holy Ghoſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſaid in the Chappel of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> and Oath taken, having four times aſſembl'd in the ſame Place, to conclude upon the Two Bulls, ſaid to have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed by our Holy Lords and Popes <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Julius</hi> III. in favour of thoſe that would be diſtinguiſh'd from Us, under the Names of the Society of JESUS; which Two Bulls the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40768:23"/> Court of Parliament ſent Us by an Uſher, to be view'd and examin'd: For which Reaſon, after we had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly examin'd and conſider'd all the Particulars,</p>
                  <p>We are of Advice, That this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, in matter of our Faith, is of dangerous Conſequence, erected to trouble the Peace of the Church, to ſubvert the State and Monaſtick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and in two words, introduc'd rather for Deſolation and Deſtruction, then for Edification.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This was the Judgment which the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> made of the Jeſuites Doctrine. But without looking back ſo far as the Year 1554. the moſt Chriſtian King need no more then conſider what paſs'd in the Year 1610. when <hi>Henry</hi> IV. was ſtabb'd by <hi>Ravillac;</hi> certainly he would then abhor that Doctrine which he now upholds with all his Royal Power, in the face of all Chriſtendom. It deſerves to be recited, becauſe it makes for our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The ſame Day that the deteſtable <hi>Ravillac</hi> was executed, in regard that in all the Anſwers which he gave the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Aix,</hi> and the Predicant <hi>Coef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feteau,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40768:23"/> during his Impriſonment, for the Parricide he had committed, he made uſe of the Maxims of <hi>Mariana</hi> and other Jeſuites, who have written, That 'twas lawful to kill Kings and Tyrants, the Court of Parliament, before they condemn'd thoſe infamous Books to be burnt by the hands of the Common Hung-man, would have the Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Faculty of Theology, and enjoin'd the Dean of the Faculty to call a Convocation, in order to give 'em their Opinion, whether it were lawful for any one, upon any Account, or for any Cauſe whatever, to attempt the ſacred Perſons of Kings and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes.</p>
            <p>Upon which, the Faculty aſſembl'd in the Colledge of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> and made the following Cenſure.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="censure">
               <body>
                  <head>The Cenſure of the Faculty of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> aſſembled in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> againſt Parricides of Kings.</head>
                  <p>IN the Year of our Lord 1610. upon the 14th of <hi>June,</hi> the ſacred Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty being aſſembl'd, and having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40768:24"/> the Queſtion to them put by the Court of Parliament; and conſidering withal that the Univerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> has been always the Mother and Nurſe of a moſt excellent and ſound Doctrine: That the Publick Repoſe and Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare proceeds from Order, and that this Order depends, next to God, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Safety of Kings and Princes: That it only belongs to the Prince, or Politick Power, to make uſe of the Sword: That ſome Years ſince, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſtrange, ſeditious and impious Opinions, have in ſuch a manner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the Minds of ſeveral People, that they have not dreaded to ſtain King and Princes with the execrable Names of Tyrants; and in purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a Pretence ſo deteſtable, as alſo under colour of aſſiſting, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing Piety, Religion, or the Publick Good, to conſpire againſt their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Perſons, and to embrue their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide-hands in Blood ſo dear, and of ſo high a Value, and conſequently to open a Gap to all ſorts of Wickedneſs, Impieties, Perſidies, Diſloyalties, Frauds, Surprizes, Treaſons, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, mutual Slaughter of the People, Ruin, ſacking and levelling of whole
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40768:24"/> Towns, Deſtruction of Provinces and flouriſhing Kingdoms; and in a word, to an infinite number of abominable Crimes, occaſion'd by Wars as well Foreign as Domeſtick: Laſtly, knowing that ſuch Peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and Diabolical Opinions, at this time, render thoſe who are ſeparated from the Catholick, Apoſtolick, and Roman Church, obſtinate in their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and cauſe 'em to avoid the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of Catholick Monks, Doctors, and Prelates, altho' innocent, as if they taught and authoriz'd ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Doctrines. For theſe and ſuch-like Reaſons, after diligent Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, the ſaid Faculty unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with a fix'd Reſolution, deteſt and condemn ſuch ſtrange and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Docrines; as impious and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, pernicious to human Society, the Publick Peace and Tranquillity, and the Catholick Religion. In te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony whereof, the ſaid Faculty have concluded and reſolved to renew their ancient Decree, put forth a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years ago, by the Advice of a hundred forty and one Divines, for the Condemnation of the following execrable Opinion.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:40768:25"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="opinion">
                     <body>
                        <p>A Tyrant, whoever he be, may and ought lawfully and meritoriouſly to be kill'd by his Vaſſal or Subject, whoever he be, by any manner of ways; chiefly by ſecret Embuſcado's, Treaſons, Flatteries, and ſuch-like Artifices, notwithſtanding any Oath or Allegiance which the Subject may have ſworn to the Tyrant; nor is it needful that he ſhould wait for, or expect the Sentence or Command of any Judge for the proſecution of his Deſign.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon which follows the Cenſure of the Faculty.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="censure">
               <body>
                  <p>This Propoſition taken thus gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and according to the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word <hi>Tyrant,</hi> is an Errour againſt the Catholick Faith, againſt the Doctrine of good Manners, and the Command of God, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> 'Tis alſo againſt the Doctrine of our Saviour, <hi>They that take up the Sword, ſhall periſh by the Sword.</hi> Moreover, it tends to the utter Subverſion and Ruin of all States, Kings and Princes in the World: It opens a Door to all manner of Impieties, Deceits, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40768:25"/> Violations of Oaths, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally give Subjects a Licence to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate all manner of Diſobedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their Soveraigns, as alſo to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty and Miſtruſt of one another, and conſequently to eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Moreover, whoever obſtinately maintains ſuch an Errour, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that may be deduc'd from this general Propoſition, is a Heretick, and ought to be puniſh'd as ſuch a one even after his Death.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Given in the Year 1413. Wedneſday, Decemb. 3.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The aforeſaid Cenſure of the Faculty of Theology of <hi>Paris,</hi> was confirm'd by the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> Anno 1415. in the Calends of <hi>July,</hi> in theſe words:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="confirmation">
               <body>
                  <p>THE Holy Council being willing to employ all their Care in the extirpation of Errours and Hereſies, budding forth in divers parts of the World, according to their Duty, and being alſo aſſembl'd for that effect, and being likewiſe inform'd, that of late years certain ſcandalous Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, erroncous in Faith, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to good Manners, and which tend
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40768:26"/> only to the ſubverſion of all Order and good Government have been taught and publiſh'd; amongſt which, this is one:
<q>That a Tyrant, whoever he be, may and ought meritoriouſly to be kill'd by his Vaſſal or Subject, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> Now the Council having a ſingular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to oppoſe this Errour, and utterly to extirpate it, after mature deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, decree, declare, and determine, That this Doctrine is erroneous in Faith, and contrary to Good Manners, and therefore reprove and condemn it as Heretical, Scandalous, opening a Gap to all manner of Deceits, Frauds, Lyes, Treaſons, Perjuries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And we farther declare, decree, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, That all who obſtinately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend this pernicious Doctrine, are He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, and ought to be puniſh'd as ſuch, according to the Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore the Sacred Faculty, after having carefully and exactly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd the Opinions of all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in general, and of each in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, is of Opinion in the firſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40768:26"/> place, That the ancient Cenſure of the ſaid Faculty, confirm'd by the ſaid Faculty, ought not only to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd, but alſo imprinted in the Minds of all Men. Secondly, that it is an Impious, Seditious, and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Thing, to attempt and lay vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands upon the ſacred Perſons of Kings and Princes, whatever Pretence any Vaſſal, Subject, or Foreigner may have or ſeek for. Thirdly, we will and decree, That all Doctors and Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelours in Divinity, upon the Day tha they uſually take their Oaths, to obſerve the Statutes and Articles of the ſaid Faculty, ſhall alſo ſwear, and alſo promiſe under their Sign Manual, to teach the Truth of this Decree, whether in their Divinity-Lectures, or in preaching the Word of God.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon this Cenſure the Parliament decreed, <q rend="inline">That the Book of <hi>John Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,</hi> entitul'd, <hi>De Rege &amp; Regis Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi> Printed both at <hi>Mayence</hi> and other Places, containing ſeveral execrable Blaſphemies againſt <hi>Henry</hi> III. of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Memory, the Perſons and States of Kings and Sovereign Princes, and other Propoſitions, contrary to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40768:27"/> Decree of the Faculty of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſhall be burnt by the Hand of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Hangman, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Accordingly <hi>Mariana</hi>'s Book was burnt by the Common Executioner, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Great Church of <hi>Paris:</hi> And all Perſons whatever were prohibited under the Penalties of High Treaſon, to Write or Print any Books or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, contrary to the ſaid Decree and Edict.</p>
            <p>Thus you have three authentick De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and the Court of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Paris,</hi> condemning the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Doctrine which teaches the Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings. But are the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits e'er a whit the more wiſe, or the leſs ſanguinary for theſe Decrees? The Two Princes, who ſo loudly declare themſelves at this day to be their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors, do they not authorize all their Maxims? Have they not, to the great Scandal of all the reſt of the Chriſtian Princes, given a new Birth to thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Monſters, whom the Prudence and Zeal of ſo many Doctors took care to ſtifle in their Infancy? The Loſs which <hi>France</hi> ſuſtain'd of Two Kings,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40768:27"/> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> III. and <hi>Henry</hi> IV. whoſe Blood was ſhed by theſe Murderers, gave an occaſion to the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> to the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; to ſtop the courſe of theſe dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Opinions, which tended to no leſs then the deſtruction of all the Crowned Heads in Chriſtian <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But at this day, I am aſham'd to ſpeak it, Kings themſelves are they who pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly authorize'em, and employ all their Forces to uphold and ſecond Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers. They make choice themſelves of the Traytors who are to deſtroy King <hi>William.</hi> Thus you ſee the <hi>Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings</hi> preach'd up anew by the Jeſuits, authoriz'd and ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all the Power of Two Monarchs, one of which holds the Firſt Rank in Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>But theſe are only the Diſciples; let us ſee what the Profeſſors of this infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Doctrine are themſelves: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that you may underſtand 'em well, I ſhall recite a Speech which the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Jeſuits made one day to the whole Crew of his Order; 'tis ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, that 'twill not be unaccept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, tho' ſet down word for word. 'Twas made when Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:40768:28"/> Reign'd in <hi>England,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Dear <hi>CHILDREN,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> know that I am now here to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand yee: Jeſus Christ, our Lord, is my Mouth; ſo that you ought to obey Me in all Things, and in all Places. God ſhed down his Holy Spirit upon our Holy Father St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> for the Support of his Church, which was juſt ready to fall thro' the violent Shoggs of <hi>Lutheran</hi> Errours, which had ſpread themſelves all over <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> to the great Grief of all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Since then it has pleaſed God that wee are this holy Man's Succeſſors, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves us, that like him, wee ſhould be the chief Workmen to extirpate the Root of Hereſies. Wee ſee theſe Hereſies reigning in ſeveral Kingdoms: On the one ſide Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in Arms against their Princes; on the other, Princes tyrannizing overtheir Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: In one place a Heretick Princeſs; and not far from her, a King of the ſame Profeſſion: Others feed us with fair Hopes and outward appearances to delude us. 'Tis for us, my dear Children, to defend the Cauſe of God and poor Subjects, not in ſhew, as our Anceſtors did, but in good earneſt.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40768:28"/> They who have hitherto taken his Duty upon 'em, have only flatter'd and tickl'd the Wound, and conſequently made it wider. It behoves us to be the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners of God's Severity, who will never be diſpleas'd, if, as the Arbitrators of his Will, we tranſlate, to the prejudice of ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governing Kings, their Kingdomes to thoſe who we ſhall know in our Conſciences to be more worthy of 'em. Now if you think your ſelves ſtrong enough of your ſelves to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute my Commands, at leaſt let this be the Leſſon which you ſhall teach in the midſt of the Church of God: You are to make uſe of Sword and Fire, for fear the Gangrene get into it. We ſhall there find, at the long-run, good Workmen and good Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. But more eſpecially apply to 'em the ſacred Inſtruments of Confeſſion, Maſſes, and Communions, to the end, that with more aſſurance of Conſcience, they may finiſh thoſe pious Works, which the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Chriſtian Affairs commands us, and to which the Duty of our Functions obliges us.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Obſerve, I pray, the Expreſſions and Terms of this Harangue: <hi>You muſt,</hi> ſays the Jeſuit, <hi>make uſe of Fire and Sword, for fear of a Gangrene.</hi> This
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40768:29"/> is an Exhortation enough to ſhake the Crowns of all good Princes at this day reigning. After this, 'tis no wonder if the moſt Chriſtian King and King <hi>James,</hi> who are as true Jeſuits in their Hearts and Souls, as was the General of their Order, who made this Speech, aſſociate in a Conſpiracy to cut off a Princes, whom the Jeſuits look upon at this day as the moſt Capital of their Enemies. A mortal Hatred, which has no other foundation then the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which that Great Monarch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes. But would to God they only aim'd at the Religion of Princes; Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory would not then recout to us the Tragical Deaths of ſo many Great Princes, who have been offer'd up as Victims to their Fury; tho' they were Roman Catholicks, and no leſs emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for their Piety and Zeal for the Propagation of the Roman Catholick Faith. Yet for all that, have they been e'er a whit the leſs ſpar'd, or e'er a jot the farther from being ſacrific'd to the Doctrine of the Jeſuits? But let us take a view of theſe Examples, for the ſatisfaction of the Reader. We have ſeen the Judgment which the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> gave of the Jeſuits, upon their reſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40768:29"/> in <hi>France:</hi> After that, we have ſeen the Doctrine which teaches the <hi>Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings,</hi> condemn'd by the Faculty of Theology at <hi>Paris,</hi> and declar'd abominable by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Conſtance;</hi> and, laſtly, <hi>Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s Books burnt by the hand of the Common Hangman, by a Decree of the Parliament of <hi>Paris.</hi> But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe Thunders launc'd againſt their Errors and their Morals, you have alſo ſeen the General of the Order's Harangue made to all the Members of the Society. Let us now come to their Executions.</p>
            <p>The firſt Tragical Example that Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory preſents us withal, is the Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Great <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> of Happy Memory. This Prince was the Object of all good Men's Love, and conſequently the Object of the Jeſuits Hatred: For the Aſſaſſines of Kings always aim at Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. A Tyrant, a Prince who wallows in his Pleaſures, and Sacrifices all things to his Ambition, is in no danger.</p>
            <p>The firſt Attempt of the Jeſuits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſacred Perſon of the great Prince <hi>William</hi> was made at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> by <hi>John Juvregni,</hi> a <hi>Spaniard</hi> by Birth. This
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40768:30"/> wicked Ruffian diſcharg'd a Pocket-Piſtol at the Prince, and wounded him in the Jaw below the Ear. Upon which, the Guard falling upon the Ruſſian with their Swords and Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berds, kill'd him immediately, which was the reaſon that the Author of ſo black an Attempt, could never be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd from the Mouth of the Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer: But the Marks that were ſhew'd upon <hi>Juvregni</hi>'s Body, made it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently apparent that the Jeſjuits were the Authors. Thoſe Marks conſiſted in a green Wax-Candle, with the Sign of the Croſs imprinted at the bottom, and a Medal ſtamp'd with the Image of the Virgin, which he carry'd upon his naked Skin, made by the Jeſuits of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> according to the Depoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of one of his Accomplices, call'd <hi>Venero,</hi> who was executed ſome time after.</p>
            <p>This Prince was look'd upon as the Head of the Hereticks and Rebels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> And the ſame Spirit, which is the Spirit of Rage and Fury, which caus'd 'em to act then, envenom'd 'em now againſt the King of <hi>England.</hi> But Vertuous Princes, who are the <hi>Nurſlings</hi> of God, as <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> ſays, or rather his enlivn'd Images,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40768:30"/> or as the Scripture calls 'em, <hi>The Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God,</hi> are in no Danger, ſo long as He takes care of their Preſervation; and it is our hopes, that the ſame Divine Power will preſerve King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> from all the Snares of his Enemies. But let us run over the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that attended this dreadful At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of <hi>Juvregni;</hi> for they are very remarkable.</p>
            <p>A certain Monk call'd Father <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merman,</hi> born in <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> formerly a <hi>Jacobin,</hi> was apprehended and put in Priſon for the ſame Fact: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examin'd by the Judges, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, That he had been bred up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> from whom he learnt the <hi>Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings.</hi> That the ſaid <hi>Juvregni</hi> coming to him, to confeſs his Deſign to kill the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> the ſaid Father <hi>Anthony</hi> declar'd, That he gave him Abſolution upon theſe Conditions:
<q>That if he did not commit the Fact for Mony, but for the Glory of God, and out of his Zeal for the Catholick Apoſtolick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, then it was lawful for him to do it, upon giving him Abſolution, after laying before him the danger that might ariſe from the Fact.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:40768:31"/>
            <p>Such are the Principles of the <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITES,</hi> and by conſequence of the Jeſuited Princes that conſpir'd againſt King <hi>WILLIAM.</hi> Forbid it Heaven, that any other Chriſtian Prince, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confederate or not Confederate, ſhould be embru'd with the ſame Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments! Moſt certain we are, that the Emperour, the K. of <hi>Spain,</hi> and all the reſt of the Princes, who at this time conſtitute the Auguſt Confederacy that has taken Arms againſt <hi>France,</hi> deteſt theſe abominable Maxims.</p>
            <p>The Publick Teſtimonies which they give of their Zeal for the Affairs of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> their particular Eſteem for the Perſon of King <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> make it apparent, that they have ſtudy'd Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in another School then that of the <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITES.</hi> And tho' the Emperour, and ſome other Catholick Princes, ſuffer 'em to reſide in their Courts; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, they take care how they liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to their Advice, as they do in <hi>France,</hi> and as they did in <hi>England</hi> while K. <hi>James</hi> Reign'd, who made choice of a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> for his chief Miniſter.</p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian King and K. <hi>James,</hi> are the only Inſtruments at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent which the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> make uſe of, to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40768:31"/> revive in Chriſtendom, thoſe dreadful Monſters, which the Wiſdom and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our preceding Kings, took ſo much care to ſtifle.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſee the end of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy form'd by the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> to cut off the Great <hi>WILLIAM.</hi> The firſt Blow failing, as we have ſet forth, yet would they not give over for all that: So that in the Year 1584. one <hi>Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar Gerard</hi> gave the fatal Stroak to that Noble Prince. He confeſs'd at his Execution, <q rend="inline">That he liv'd privately with a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> whoſe Name he knew not, only that he was a Red-hair'd Man, Regent of the Colledge-of <hi>Treves,</hi> who aſſur'd him, That he had Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated his Enterprize to three of his Companions, who found it to the ALL FROM GOD; and before he left 'em, gave him their Benediction, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaining him withal, that if he dy'd in the Attempt, he ſhould be put into the Kalendar of Martyrs.</q> And with this Confeſſion in his Mouth he dy'd.</p>
            <p>After this bloody Scene, the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> who had ſworn the Extirpation of the Auguſt Family of the Princes of <hi>Orange,</hi> made an Attempt upon the Son of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40768:32"/> Great <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> who was Prince <hi>Maurice. Furor Arma miniſtrat.</hi> The Spirit of Blood which puſh't 'em for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, excited 'em to ſuborn an infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Monſter, whoſe Name as <hi>Poter Panne,</hi> a Cooper, who undertook to Aſſaſſinate this Prince: But Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which does not always permit the Wicked to proſper in their ungodly Enterprizes, ſo order'd it, that <hi>Peter Panne</hi> was apprehended juſt as he was about to have dipt his hands in the Blood of the Great <hi>Maurice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Offender was executed at <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> the 22d of <hi>June</hi> 1598. and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Death confeſt, That the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> of <hi>Doway</hi> had ſet him on to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that Murther, upon promiſe of a Prebendary for his Son: And that when the Father Provincial gave him his Benediction, he embrac'd him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe words, <hi>Go my dear Friend in Peace, for you go like an Angel under the Protection of God,</hi> and dy'd with this Depoſition in his Mouth.</p>
            <p>Theſe Attempts upon the Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of theſe two Princes, make it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt, That the famous Maſters who teach the <hi>Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings,</hi> have had a ſtrange Hatred from
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40768:32"/> time to time, againſt the Illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Orange;</hi> ſo that 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if it now break out again in the Treaſon ſo lately contriv'd againſt the Perſon of King <hi>WILLIAM.</hi> One would think, that all Hell were let looſe againſt that Prince; nor is it to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that the Fury of theſe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd Ruffians will ever be at an end, unleſs tyr'd out and waſted by exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>However, 'tis a ſingular Proof of the continual Care, that Providence takes for the preſervation of this Great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, that all the deteſtable Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which theſe Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> contrive againſt his Perſon, are ſtill diſcover'd, to the eternal Infamy of the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, thereby render'd odious to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity to all truly Chriſtian Princes. 'Tis a foul piece of Treachery, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy a moſt Chriſtian Monarch, to ſeek the deſtruction of his Enemy by ways ſo deteſtable. For whatever Shifts and Evaſious <hi>France</hi> may uſe to ward off the Reproach which all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom has at this day juſt reaſon to throw upon her, ſhe will never be able to clear her ſelf. She has got too bad a Name already for the Cruelties ſhe has exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis'd
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40768:33"/> upon her moſt faithful Subjects, and the Princes her Neighbours; ſo that ſhe had little need to have added this ſtain of Infamy to the Nation, and render her ſelf more obnoxious in all the reſt of the Courts of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>After Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> the Greateſt and the moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Princeſs of her Time, was in danger of loſing her Life by the Fury of the ſame Aſſaſſinators.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Parry,</hi> by Birth an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, and a Doctor of the Civil Law, was the deteſtable Inſtrument made choice of by the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> to attempt the Life of that Princeſs. This <hi>William Parry</hi> had ſpent his Life in all manner of looſeneſs and Debauchery, till he had waſted his Eſtate, and reduc'd his Family to the Hoſpital: So that not being able to ſubſiſt in <hi>England,</hi> he took a reſolution to travel into <hi>Ota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Where being arriv'd at <hi>Venice,</hi> and not knowing what courſe to take for a Livelihood, his evil Star carry'd him to Father <hi>Benedict Palmin,</hi> a <hi>Jeſuite;</hi> a Man of great Reputation among the Members of his Order, with whom he entered into a ſtrict League of Amity.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:40768:33"/>
            <p>After ſome few days Acquaintance, it came into <hi>Parry</hi>'s mind to propoſe to the <hi>Jeſuite</hi> the making an Attempt upon the Sacred Perſon of Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> in hopes to gain the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one whom he deſired for a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron in a ſtrange Countrey, where he had no Acquaintance, or elſe to ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize himſelf in the World by ſome remarkable Action.</p>
            <p>With theſe thoughts he propos'd to the <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> the killing of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> his natural Princeſs, and the ſetting up in her room <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scotland,</hi> a Roman Catholick. This Propoſal was well lik'd by Father <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> who extreamly encourag'd and applauded his Zeal, telling him, That there was nothing but Delay that could diſappoint ſo noble and ſo pious a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, that would acquire him not only a great Reputation in this World, but a bleſſed Immortality in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Parry</hi> conſidering that time was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, leaves <hi>Italy,</hi> and comes to <hi>Lyon,</hi> where he was to deliver Father <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins</hi> Letters to the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> of that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and where having open'd his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, he was receiv'd by the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> with all the kindneſs imaginable, telling
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40768:34"/> him, That they lookt upon him as the Reſtorer of the Catholick Apoſtolick Religion in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after they had bleſs'd him, and fortify'd him as much as lay in their power, for the execution of ſuch a holy Act, they gave him Letters to Father <hi>Coldrett</hi> a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> in the Colledge at <hi>Paris,</hi> to whom upon his Arrival, he confeſs'd himſelf; and after he had imparted to him his Deſign, Father <hi>Coldrette</hi> gave him his Benediction, applauded his Zeal for the Propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Faith, and gave him all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Inſtructions for the ſpeedy Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his Deſign.</p>
            <p>This done, the holy Apoſtle depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>England,</hi> and came to <hi>London,</hi> where he ſo order'd his buſineſs that he got to be admitted into the Queens Preſence; and the better to inſinuate himſelf into her Favour, he feign'd to make her Privy to a Conſpiracy which the Roman Catholicks were weaving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Life, and that he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to enter into the Plot on purpoſe to ſound 'em; of all which he thought it his Duty to inform her Majeſty. And this deteſtable Murtherer told his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40768:34"/> Tale with ſo much Probability, that the Queen gave credit to it; ſo much the rather, becauſe it agreed with the Intelligence which ſhe had receiv'd from <hi>France,</hi> of a Deſign that was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving againſt her Perſon.</p>
            <p>All this while, Heaven preſerv'd this Illuſtrious Princeſs: For tho' <hi>Parry</hi> wanted neither Opportunity nor Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, for the Execution of his dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Enterprize, yet Providence would not permit him to accompliſh it. At length the Traytor imparted his thoughts to one <hi>Nevill,</hi> a Roman Catholick, in hopes of his Aſſiſtance; but he, deteſting ſo horrid a Crime, kept <hi>Parry</hi> in ſuſpenſe, and flatter'd him with fair Hopes, till he could find an Opportunity to inform the Queen, who order'd both to be apprehended, returning Thanks to Heaven for her Deliverance, from ſo great a Danger. Upon which, <hi>Parry</hi> being examin'd, confeſs'd the whole Matter with all the Circumſtances, as we have here ſet 'em down; ſo that he was Executed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 2d. of <hi>March</hi> 1584.</p>
            <p>Such was the end of this Martyr, who the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> had taken ſo much care to inſtruct, in order to the taking
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40768:35"/> out of the World a Princeſs no leſs then belov'd, for her Zeal and Piety, then King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> is now for his Heroic Vertues.</p>
            <p>But as the moſt Chriſtian King and King <hi>James,</hi> true <hi>Jeſuites</hi> as they are, diſdain to give over for a Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, never aweary of returning to the Charge, ſo that there hardly paſſes a Campagne without ſome new Attempt to cut off King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> by treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Violence: So in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> time, hardly one Conſpiracy was diſcover'd, but the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> were ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting another on Foot.</p>
            <p>For in the Year 1595. one <hi>Edward Squire,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man by Birth, and a Proteſtant, embarking in Sir <hi>F. Drakes</hi> Fleet, which was bound for <hi>America;</hi> the Ship wherein he was, being ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by bad Weather, was taken by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and he carry'd into <hi>Spain</hi> a Priſoner of War. In that Diſtreſs he fell into the Acquaintance of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Richard Walpote,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, who in hopes of making him change his Religion, procur'd his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. Which, when <hi>Squire</hi> after he had got his Liberty, refus'd to do, he
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40768:35"/> playd him a <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Trick indeed, and clapt him up in the Inquiſition; which prov'd ſo unſupportable to him, that he ſacrific'd his Religion to his Liberty: After which Change, <hi>Walpote</hi> was ſo much the ſole Maſter of his Will and Inclinations, that he eaſily inſtill'd into him the Villanous Sentiments of the Society. When he had him ſure, he propos'd to him the making an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon the Perſon of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth;</hi> adding, that it would be an Action pleaſing to God, and by which he would certainly merit Paradice. Thus gain'd, he receiv'd the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> laſt Orders, how to regulate himſelf; he confeſs'd, and receiv'd the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. At what time Father <hi>Walpote</hi> giving the Ruffian his Benediction, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd him, and after he had loaded his For head with a Thouſand Signs of the Croſs, <hi>Go Son,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>God bleſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and ſtrengthen thee; be of good Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, I engage my Soul for thine, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live or dead, thou ſhalt have a ſhare in my Prayers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, he put into his hands a Poyſon, enclos'd within two Piggs Bladders, with Orders not to touch it without Gloves, for fear of poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40768:36"/> himſelf: Which Poiſon was to be rubb'd upon the Pummel of the Queens Saddle, or the Elbow of her Chair of State, as he could find his beſt Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. But while <hi>Squire</hi> was ſlow in his Performance, or elſe was diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of meeting convenient Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, <hi>Walpote,</hi> who was impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to hear of the Succeſs of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple, nor receiving any Intelligence from him, and therefore believing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf betray'd and gull'd, while he medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated Revenge upon <hi>Squire,</hi> was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the occaſion of the Diſcovery: For he immediately ſent away an <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man from <hi>Spain,</hi> with directions that he ſhould pretend that he had made his Eſcape out of the Inquiſition, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy. Which he did in good earneſt. Whereupon the Queen caus'd <hi>Squire</hi> to be ſought for, and apprehended: And being thus in hold, he was ſoon convicted and condemned; and at the Place of Execution, diſcover'd who was the Perſon that had ſet him at work.</p>
            <p>Nor was this the laſt Attempt upon the Life of that vertuous Princeſs; for that during the whole courſe of her Reign, ſhe eſcap'd moſt terrible Snares,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40768:36"/> and many wicked Contrivances againſt her Life: So that if Divine Providence had not had a particular care of her Life, ſhe muſt infallibly have been hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd, by ſome violent Death, out of the World. Nor has Heaven ſhew'd leſs ſurprizing Wonders in the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the ſacred Perſon of King <hi>William;</hi> of whom it may be ſaid, that he has no ſooner eſcap'd one Danger, but another threatens him.</p>
            <p>Now all the Tragical Events, all the Conſpiracies before recited, have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd their Original from the Jeſuits: They were the Perſons who firſt preach'd to the World the <hi>Art of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſinating Kings.</hi> Whence I conclude, that 'tis no wonder if at this very day we find the moſt Chriſtian King and King <hi>James</hi> aſſociated together in ſuch a horrid Cabal, as has been lately diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, ſeeing they are more Jeſuits then Kings.</p>
            <p>But it will be objected, That Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was of the Reformed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and King <hi>William</hi> is of the ſame Religion; no wonder then the Jeſuits cabal againſt 'em. To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That if Religion were the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that could only juſtifie Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40768:37"/> and Aſſaſſinations, how came it to paſs that <hi>Henry</hi> III. and <hi>Henry</hi> IV. who were both Roman Catholick Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, could not 'ſcape the being made Victims to the Fury of the ſame Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers. <hi>Henry</hi> III. was a Monk in his Sentiments, and in all his Conduct; witneſs the cruel Maſſacre of St. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew,</hi> of which he was the Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Henry</hi> IV. had chang'd his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Nevertheleſs the Blood of theſe Two Princes was ne'er the leſs ſpar'd; nor were they Both, the One and the Other, ne'er the leſs the Objects of the Jeſuits Fury, then King <hi>William,</hi> who is a Reformed Prince.</p>
            <p>'Tis not then the Religion of Princes that gives an occaſion to theſe fatal Conſpiracies againſt their ſacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but rather a Spirit of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Jealouſie, Ambition, Fury, and unbridled Zeal, which animates the deteſtable Authors; who teach, that Princes are to be aſſaſſinated, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to comply with their Deſigns and Purpoſes, and ſtudy their Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the moſt Chriſtian King and King <hi>James</hi> have done.</p>
            <p>After this, I leave it to the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all good Catholick Princes,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40768:37"/> whoſe Intereſts are ſo cloſely united to thoſe of the Proteſtant Princes, ſince they fight at this day for the ſame Cauſe, which is to free their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions from the Tyranny of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy; I leave it, I ſay, to their Conſideration, whether they will be leſs expos'd to clandeſtine Attempts, for being Good Catholicks, then the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>The Barbarous Act which the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators ſo lately projected againſt the Perſon of King <hi>William,</hi> is a Fact which at this day concerns all Crowned Heads. The Emperour, the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and all the reſt of the Catholick Princes, are engag'd to exclaim ſo loudly againſt this deteſtable Enterprize, that the moſt Chriſtian King, and King <hi>James,</hi> may loſe all Thoughts of attempting the like, unleſs they deſire to be look'd upon as the moſt odious of Princes that ever Reign'd among Chriſtians or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. I dare be alſo bold to ſay, That in reſpect of the Bloody Outrage which they have offer'd Religion and all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, the Catholick Princes are in ſome meaſure oblig'd to excite the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40768:38"/> Pope to launce out all the Thunder of the <hi>Vatican</hi> againſt theſe Monarchs, with Threats of Excommunication, if they beg not Pardon of God and the Church, for ſo black an Attempt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> the Deciſions of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne,</hi> and the Decree of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> before recited.</p>
            <p>Well: After to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the next Prince that preſents himſelf upon the Jeſuits Bloody Theater, is <hi>Henry</hi> IV. who ſucceeded next after the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> III. who was a true Roman Catholick, more Monk then King, but yet aſſaſſinated by <hi>James Clement. Henry</hi> IV. had chang'd his Religion; and yet wee find he had no more Mercy ſhew'd him then his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1593. <hi>Peter Barriere,</hi> born at <hi>Orleans,</hi> being a Souldier in one of the Regiments of the <hi>Gens d'Armes,</hi> a Fancy took him to kill the King, out of a belief that he ſhould do God good Service; which is always the gilded Pretence of theſe infamous Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſines.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40768:38"/> To this purpoſe away he goes to <hi>Melun,</hi> where the Court then was; but upon intelligence given the King, grounded only upon a bare Suſpicion, the Miſcreant was apprehended at the Gate of the City: There was found about him a Knife much like a <hi>Baionette,</hi> which the Grenadiers in <hi>France</hi> make uſe of at this day. And this Knife was deſign'd for the fatal Blow that was to have been given the King.</p>
            <p>Upon this, he was brought to his Trial; and being convicted of High Treaſon, was condemn'd to die: And at the Place of Execution he confeſs'd, That being at <hi>Lions,</hi> he had conſulted four Religious Perſons, one Carmelite, one Jacobin, one Capuchin, and one Jeſuit; who after they had carefully enjoin'd him Secreſie, gave him their Benediction, and confirm'd him in the Reſolution he had taken. With that, away he went for <hi>Paris,</hi> and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately apply'd himſelf to the Curate of St. <hi>Adnrews des Arts,</hi> a troubleſom Fellow, and an Adherent to the League.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:40768:39"/>
            <p>After he had made him privy to the Enterprize, he applauded it extreamly; but advis'd him above all things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr with the Rector of the Jeſuits, which was done. The Rector aſſur'd him, that the Deſign which he had laid, was all from God; that it behoved him only to have a good Courage, to Confeſs himſelf, and receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Afterwards, the Rector car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd him into his Chamber, and after he had given him his laſt Inſtructions, gave him alſo his Benediction.</p>
            <p>The next day he was confeſs'd by another Jeſult, and received the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He alſo imparted his Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize to a Third of the ſame Order, who was a great Preacher, and a great Stickler in the Rebellion againſt the King, who approv'd his Reſolution as moſt Holy and Meritorious. Upon which Approbation, he bought the Knife that was found about him, the Point of which he caus'd to be ground for the purpoſe; and in purſuance of his deteſtable Deſigns, he follow'd the King to <hi>Melun,</hi> where he was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:40768:39"/>
            <p>Beſides this Confeſſion, his Anſwers to the Interrogatories, put more home to him by his Judges, are ſuch as ought to make all Princes aſham'd, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare themſelves to be Favourers of the Jeſuits. For being ask'd where he had learn'd that New Theology, which taught him to Murder Kings? He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>That he was taught by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy.</hi> Being ask'd, Whether he had never ſtudied in the Colledge of Jeſuits? He anſwer'd, <hi>Yes; under Father</hi> Gueret, <hi>with whom he had been two Years and a half.</hi> Being ask'd, whether he had been in the Chamber of Meditations, into which the Jeſuites carry their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Sinners, to ſhew 'em ſeveral dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Portraitures of Devils, under vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Figures, thereby pretending to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce 'em to a better Life, or rather to diſlocate and diſorder their Minds, and prepare them by terrible Viſions for ſome bloody Undertaking? He anſwer'd, <hi>That he had often been in the Chamber of Meditations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being ask'd whether he had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to murder the King; he anſwer'd, <hi>That he had been told, it was a laudable
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40768:40"/> Thing to kill the King; and that they who told him ſo, call'd him Tyrant.</hi> Being ask'd, whether ſuch Propoſals and Maxims as theſe were not often in the mouths of the Jeſuites? He made anſwer, <hi>That he had heard 'em ſay, that it was lawful to kill the King: That he was not to be obey'd nor look'd upon as King, till he was abſolv'd by the Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the Confeſſion of this noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Offender, before all the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers aſſembl'd in a Body: And being upon the Wheel, he ſaid, <hi>There were still two ſwarthy Prieſts, whoſe Names he knew not, who were departed from</hi> Lyons, <hi>upon the ſame Deſign; but that he aim'd to have got before 'em, that he might have had all the Honour of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Barrier</hi> having miſs'd his Blow, the Jeſuites would not ſtop there: They had determin'd the King's Death, and therefore no means muſt be left uneſſay'd to cut him off. Not much unlike the Blood-thirſty Proſecution of Conſpiracy upon Conſpiracy, againſt the ſacred Perſon of King <hi>William</hi> at
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40768:40"/> this day. But that which is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd at, in the Proceedings of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators now a-days, is this: That they are authoriz'd and protected by two Chriſtian Princes; whereas in the Attempts laid againſt <hi>Henry</hi> IV. the Jeſuites alone were the principal Actors. The next Monſter therefore whom they made choice of, after <hi>Barrier,</hi> to attempt the Life of that Renowned Prince, was <hi>John Chaſtel,</hi> a young Stripling, about nineteen Years of Age, who had been brought up in the Colledge of the Jeſuites; and this was a Maſter-piece of the Morality which he learnt among 'em. Upon the 27th of <hi>December,</hi> 1594. he ſought an opportunity to put his Enterprize in execution. The King being at the <hi>Louvre, Chaſtel</hi> found a way to get himſelf admitted among the Courtiers, and to get near the King, who was then diſcourſing very pleaſantly with ſeveral of the Great Lords; at what time, he ſo well took his time, that he ſtruck his Majeſty in the Mouth with his Knife, without being perceiv'd; which put all the Lords into a moſt terrible Conſternation, not knowing from whence the fatal Blow came.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:40768:41"/>
            <p>In the mean time, the Ruffian taking his advantage of this Diſorder, cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dropt the Knife, and thruſt himſelf into the Crowd, as if he had done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, in hopes to have made his eſcape. However, the Courtiers, who were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in ſearching after the Aſſaſſine, ſeiz'd upon this ſame Stranger at a venture, being no otherwiſe aſſur'd whether he were guilty or not. Nevertheleſs, he was no ſooner apprehended, but he confeſs'd the Crime. Upon which, the Parliament made a Decree, wherein the Jeſuites are ſo well ſet forth to the Life, as one would think ſhould be anough to make all Princes aſham'd, that ſuffer 'em in their Courts and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; particularly <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and <hi>James</hi> II. who make 'em their Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, their Counſellors, and their Chief Miniſters of State.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="decree">
               <body>
                  <p>The Court of Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeen the Proceſs exhibited a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>John Chaſtel,</hi> &amp;c. Student in the Jeſuites Colledge at <hi>Clermont,</hi> &amp;c. for High Treaſon, and a thrice exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable and abominable Parricide, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted upon the Perſon of the King;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40768:41"/> as alſo againſt <hi>John Gueret,</hi> ſtiling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the Society of Jeſus, and formerly the ſaid <hi>John Chaſtel</hi>'s Tutor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And finding that the Criminal Court has attainted and convicted the ſaid <hi>John Chaſtel</hi> of High Treaſon againſt God and Man, by the moſt wicked and moſt deteſtable Attempt upon the King's Perſon: And that for the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the ſaid Crime, the ſaid Court has condemn'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the Parliament farther or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains. That all the Prieſts and Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in the Colledge of <hi>Clermont,</hi> and all others ſtiling themſelves of the ſaid Society; as <hi>Corrupters of Youth, Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Publick Repoſe, Enemies to the King and Kingdom,</hi> depart out of <hi>Paris,</hi> within three days after Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this preſent Decree, and out of all Cities and Places where they have any Colledges; and within fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days after, quite out of the Realm, upon pain of being puniſh'd as Criminals, and guilty of High Treaſon. And all their Goods, as well immovable as movable, ſhall be laid out in pious Uſes. Moreover, all
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40768:42"/> the King's Subjects are forbid to ſend any Scholars to any of their Colledges without the Kingdom, upon pain of incurring the Penalties of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Having thus given you a deſcription of the Diſciple, let us take a view of the Maſters in the <hi>Art of Aſſaſſinating Princes. John Guignard,</hi> a Jeſuite, who was Regent of the Colledge of <hi>Clermont,</hi> was apprehended by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners whom the Parliament ſent to the Colledge of <hi>Clermont,</hi> to ſeize the Papers of that infamous Profeſſor, among which they found ſeveral writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with his own hand; wherein he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, That it was lawful to aſſaſſinate <hi>Henry</hi> III. and gave Inſtructions in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the murder of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. Upon which, the Parliament made another ſignal Decree, bearing date the 7th. of <hi>January,</hi> 1595.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="decree">
               <body>
                  <p>Having ſeen the Criminal Proceſs exhibited againſt <hi>John Guignard,</hi> Prieſt and Regent of the Colledge of <hi>Clermont,</hi> in this City of <hi>Paris,</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner for ſeveral Treatiſes by him
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40768:42"/> written, and containing among other things, the Approbation of the moſt cruel and inhuman Murder of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed King; and Motives to induce others to murder the King now Reigning, the Interrogatories and Confeſſion of the ſaid <hi>Guignard,</hi> the ſaid Book repreſented and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to have been compos'd by him, and written with his own Hand: It ſhall be ſaid, That the Court has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, and does declare the ſaid <hi>Guig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> attainted and convicted of High Treaſon, for having compos'd and written the ſaid Books, containing ſeveral falſe and ſeditious Arguments to prove, That it was a laudable thing to commit the ſaid Parricide upon the Perſon of <hi>Henry</hi> III. and that it was lawful to kill <hi>Henry</hi> IV. at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Reigning, for which he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to the <hi>Amende Honourable,</hi> naked in his Shirt, with a Rope about his Neck, before the principal Gate of the City of <hi>Paris,</hi> and there upon his Knees, holding a lighted Wax-Taper weighing two Pounds in his Hands, to ſay and declare,</p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:40768:43"/>
                  <p>That wickedly, villanouſly, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth, he has written, That the deceaſed King was juſtly kill'd by <hi>James Clement;</hi> and, That if the Reigning King did not die in the Wars, he ought alſo to be murder'd: Of which he repents, and begs Pardon of God, the King, and Juſtice. Which done, he is to be carry'd to the Publick Place of Execution, and there to be hang'd and ſtrangl'd upon a Gibbet ſet up on purpoſe; after which, his Body to be conſum'd to Aſhes in a Fire kindled at the foot of the Gibbet, and all his Goods to be confiſcate to the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After ſuch an authentick Piece, which ſo fully expoſes the Blackneſs of the Crimes, which the Authors of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that teaches the <hi>Art of Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Princes,</hi> commit in the World, what is there which all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> have not reaſon to fear; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when this Doctrine is authoriz'd and ſupported with all the Fury and Power of the moſt Chriſtian King, and the utmoſt of King <hi>James</hi>'s Ability.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:40768:43"/>
            <p>Should this continue, there is nothing to be expected but Butchery and Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre all over <hi>Europe;</hi> and a Pious, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonaire, Magnanimous Prince, belov'd by his Subjects, muſt always carry Death in his Boſom. All human Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence will not be able to preſerve him from the Attempts of Conſpirators. Nor does it concern Proteſtant Princes alone, but the Roman Catholicks alſo, to be careful of their own Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The 10th. of the ſame Month, the Parliament iſſu'd forth another Edict, againſt <hi>Peter Chaſtel,</hi> the Father of <hi>John Chaſtel,</hi> and <hi>John Gueret,</hi> the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, who was <hi>John</hi>'s Maſter. The Subſtance of which Edict was, That <hi>John Gueret</hi> ſhould be baniſh'd for ever; and that <hi>Peter Chaſtel,</hi> the Father of the Ruffian, ſhould pay a Forfeiture of 2000 Livres, be baniſh'd for Nine Years out of the Kingdom; that his Houſe ſhould be pull'd down, and the Place be conſecrated to publick Uſe, with a Prohibition that it ſhould never be built upon again: That a Pillar of Free-ſtone ſhould be erected upon the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40768:44"/> void Space, with a Plate, repreſenting in large Characters the deteſtable Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide committed upon <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. to render the Memory of the Authors and Inſtruments, which the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> made uſe of, to commit ſo black and enormous an Action, infamous to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity.</p>
            <p>In purſuance of this Edict, a Pillar was Erected before one of the Gates of the Palace, upon the Bridge call'd, <hi>Pont au Change,</hi> where the Ruffians Houſe ſtood, and there remain'd till the Return of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> into <hi>France.</hi> Nevertheleſs, this mark of Ignominy did no way diſcourage the <hi>Jeſuites. Barrier</hi> and <hi>Chaſtel</hi> had miſs'd of their Blow, and therefore the Authors who ſet 'em at work, enrag'd that they had not atton'd their Fury by the total Effuſion of that renowned Prince's Blood, reſolv'd to make a thild At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon his Life.</p>
            <p>But before we recount the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Aſſaſſination of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. let us ſpeak one word concorning <hi>James Clement,</hi> who Aſſaſſinated <hi>Hen.</hi> III.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40768:44"/> Till the Death of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. there was ſome reaſon to queſtion, who were the true Authors that ſet <hi>James Clement</hi> to work; for that as ſoon as ever he had ſtruck the Stroak, he was kill'd by the Guards of <hi>Hen.</hi> III. which was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that it could never be underſtood from the mouth of the Murtherer, who were the Authors and Accomplices of that deteſtable Action.</p>
            <p>But the Death of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd not long after that of <hi>Hen.</hi> III. unfolds the Riddle, and gave Juſtice thoſe Illuſtrations which ſhe was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of before. 'Twas then found that the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> were the Perſons who had embru'd their Parricide Hands in the Blood of that Prince. <hi>James Clement</hi> had been a Student in their Colledge, where he had learnt their Doctrine, and after all his great Learning, was become a <hi>Jacobin.</hi> Nor will it be amiſs to take a view of the Memoirs which the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite Guignard</hi> had drawn up and which afterwards fell into the Hands of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Cruel</hi> Nero, ſays he, ſpeaking
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40768:45"/> of <hi>Hen.</hi> III. <hi>was kill'd by one</hi> Clement, <hi>and the counterfeit</hi> Monk <hi>fell by the Hands of a true</hi> Monk. <hi>The Heroick Act perform'd by</hi> James Clement, <hi>as a</hi> Gift of the Holy Spirit, ſo call'd by us Divines, <hi>is juſtly applauded by the Prior of the</hi> Jacobins, <hi>Confeſſor and Martyr; and the Crown of</hi> France <hi>ought to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into another Family then that of the</hi> Bourbons: <hi>And the</hi> Bearnois, <hi>meaning</hi> Hen. IV. <hi>will be treated a little more gently then he deſerves, if they give him a Monks Crown in ſome well reform'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, there to repent for the Calamities he has brought upon</hi> France, <hi>and to thank God for being ſo favourable to him as to ſpare him an opportunity to know himſelf. And if he cannot be depos'd without a War, let 'em make War upon him; and if it cannot be done by War, let him be kill'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us obſerve the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this great Princes Death, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable through the Conformity which they had with what ſo lately paſs'd in the intended Aſſaſſination of of King <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> had not God in his mercy averted the fatal Stroak, by the Diſcovery of the Conſpiracy.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:40768:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Heury</hi> IV. had reſolv'd upon the day of his Coronation, and of the Publick Entry of the Queen his Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, to give ſome marks of his Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency to the Priſoners of the <hi>Bastile;</hi> and to render the Act ſo much the more Auguſt, he laid a Deſign of going in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. To which purpoſe between three and four a Clock in the Afternoon, his Majeſty took Coach at the Entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Louvre,</hi> admitting only the Dukes of <hi>Eſpernon, Monthaſon, Roquelaure,</hi> and three other Lords, to go along with him, who rode altogether in the Kings Coach; the Guards being forbid to follow him.</p>
            <p>That Order, and that moment of Time prov'd fatal to the Life of that magnanimous Prince. For <hi>Ravilliac,</hi> as he declar'd himſelf at the place of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, having a long time before pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated the Aſſaſſination of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, follow'd him to the Street, call'd <hi>La Rue de la Ferronerie,</hi> before St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> Church-Yard, where ſeeing the King's Coach ſtopp'd by ſome Carts, and the Monarch leaning toward the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> with whom he was
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40768:46"/> in Diſcourſe, the Monſter animated by the Devil, got up upon the Fore-wheel of the Coach, and with his Knife made on purpoſe, gave the King two Stabs into the Breaſt, and bereav'd him of his Life in the midſt of his Braveſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals. Both which Blows wore given with that ſwiftneſs, that they were hardly perceiv'd. The firſt enter'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his fifth and ſixth Rib, pierc'd his Heart, and reach'd the hollow Vein, which being cut, that great Prince loſt his Speech and his Life both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. As for the ſecond, it only ras'd the Skin, without any more hurt.</p>
            <p>No body ſaw the Blow Struck; ſo that if the Parricide had but flung away the Knife, it could never have been known who was the Author of that deteſtable Fact. Preſently the ſix Lords that were with the King alighted, and ſome ſought for the Parricide, while others went to help the King; but one of 'em ſeeing he had loſt his Speech, and that the Blood ran out of his mouth, cry'd out, <hi>The King is Dead.</hi> Upon which words, the People were all in a hurry, and ſuch a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40768:46"/> terrible Deſpair ſeiz'd 'em, that they threw themſelves into the Shops adjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as if the City had been taken by the Enemy.</p>
            <p>One of the Lords obſerving the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, bethought himſelf of giving it out, That the King was only wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that he was fallen into a ſwoon. They call'd for Wine, and while they ran to fetch it, they pull'd down the Boots of the Coach, telling the People, That ſeeing the King was only wounded, they would have him carry'd back to the <hi>Louvre</hi> to be dreſs't.</p>
            <p>The Queen in her Cabinet, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the doleful Tidings, over-whelm'd with ſorrow, and in a ſtrange Conſternation was going to meet the Body of her dear Monarch; but being met by the Chancellor, he put a ſtop to her. Upon whoſe approach, the Queen all in Tears, cry'd out, <hi>Alas, the King is Dead!</hi> To whom the Chancellor, without the leaſt Diſorder in his Countenance, becauſe the Affairs of the Kingdom then requir'd it: <hi>Your Majeſty muſt excuſe me, Kings never die
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40768:47"/> in</hi> France: And ſo having perſuaded her to return into her Cabinet, <hi>We muſt have a care,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>leaſt our Tears ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Affairs deſperate; we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them till another time. There are thoſe that weep both for You and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s. 'Tis for your Majeſty to take care both of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and your ſelf; We have need of Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and not of Tears.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After ſuch a fatal Stroak which put all <hi>France</hi> in Mourning, it may be ſaid, That the Rage of the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> who had the greateſt ſhare in the Fact, was in ſome meaſure aſſuag'd. Tho' when we conſider the Benefits which they had receiv'd from that Prince, and the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Proofs of his Clemency which he had given 'em, ſince their being recall'd into <hi>France,</hi> who would have thought this Monarch ſhould have been a Victim to their Fury?</p>
            <p>In the Year 1625. in the Month of <hi>May,</hi> this Prince had given 'em leave to pull down the Pyramid erected be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Palace in the Place where <hi>John Chaſtel</hi> was born, who had been a Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in their Colledge, and was ſet up for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40768:47"/> an Eternal Monument of Infamy to the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> who had ſet 'em on to attempt the Life of this Prince. For on the top of the Pillar, were to be ſeen Plates of Marble, whereon were Engrav'd in Letters of Gold, the Decree of the Court of Parliament againſt <hi>John Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel</hi> and the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> and over the four Corners, were ſet up four Statues of four Vertues.</p>
            <p>There was reaſon enough to believe, That this Monument would have ſtood many Ages; but the King, in hopes that the Remembrance of his Favours, would have engag'd the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> to live more Chriſtian like for the future, out of a Horror which they ought to have had, of ſo many Attempts againſt his Life, commanded the Lieutenant Civil, <hi>Miron</hi> to cauſe it to be pull'd down, and to Erect a Fountain in the ſame place, which was done.</p>
            <p>The more Curious were pleas'd to ſay, when the four Statues were pull'd down, among which was the Statue of <hi>Justice,</hi> That <hi>Juſtice</hi> had erected the Pillar, but that the King's Clemency
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40768:48"/> had pull'd it down. On the other ſide, they who abhorr'd the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that Taught the Aſſaſſination of Princes, made the four following Verſes:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SIR,</hi> if you needs will blot from Time to come</l>
                  <l>The Memory of th' Aſſaſſin <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtel</hi>'s Doom,</l>
                  <l>By Monument pull'd down, that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> did ordain,</l>
                  <l>It is but juſt to have Your <note n="*" place="bottom">For <hi>Chaſtel</hi> with the force of the Blow, ſtruck out one of the King's Teeth.</note> Tooth again.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding this, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe was publiſh'd or written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> that Monarch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſever'd in giving 'em all the marks ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, of his Goodneſs and Clemency, which laſted till the end of his Life. Three Weeks alſo before he was Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by <hi>Ravaillac,</hi> he ſent for the Braſs Plate from the Printer <hi>John le Clerc,</hi> which was made in the Year 1595. to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40768:48"/> the end there might not remain the leaſt Footſtep of their Infamy.</p>
            <p>So many Illuſtrious Proofs of that Princes Love toward thoſe perfidious People, plainly demonſtrate to us on the one ſide, the natural Inclination of that Prince to do good; and on the other, the Infidelity and Treachery of thoſe Authors who teach the Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings, and who were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſatisfy'd till they had embru'd their Parricide Hands in the Blood of their Benefactor.</p>
            <p>We muſt therefore conclude, from all that has been ſaid, concerning the cruel Aſſaſſination of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. complotted by the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> and put in execution by the deteſtable <hi>Ravaillac,</hi> that ſo long as there are any <hi>Jeſuites</hi> in the world, the Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings will be taught in the World; and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Principle, every good Roman Catholick Prince as well as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, will be expos'd to the Fury of theſe Aſſaſſinates. So that all Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs or Soveraigns in <hi>Europe,</hi> who are not the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> Friends, or rather
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40768:49"/> who are not the Executors of their exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Deſigns, or who contemn their Counſels in matters of Religion, have no more to do, then only to make their Wills, and prepare betimes for Death.</p>
            <p>As for the moſt Chriſtian King and K. <hi>James,</hi> they are in no Danger. Thoſe two Princes are the Societies Pupils; they'le be ſure to die a natural Death. Which is the reaſon, that both thoſe Monarchs, in acknowledgment, are ſo prodigal of their Favours to the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites.</hi> The Society propoſes to 'em, the Deſtruction of a Heretick Prince by Sword or Poyſon. Now King <hi>WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM</hi> is lookt upon by thoſe Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, as the Reſtorer of <hi>Calviniſm,</hi> the Deliverer of the Oppreſſed <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the Inſtrument whom God at this day makes uſe of, to free all <hi>Europe</hi> from the Fetters of <hi>French</hi> Slavery. This is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to render him Odious to the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,</hi> and by conſequence, to their Protectors <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, and <hi>James</hi> the Little.</p>
            <p>Therefore, according to the cruel Maxims of theſe Aſſaſſines of Kings,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40768:49"/> there is nothing to be omitted that may haſten the Deſtruction of this Great Prince. And this is the Source and Spring of the Conſpiracy ſo lately diſcover'd, and the Fatal Original of all the Attempts upon his Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſince his coming to the Throne of Great <hi>Britain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Politicians of the Times will ſay, wherefore do the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> attempt the Perſons of Roman Catholick Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Princes who were the ſworn and irreconcilable Enemies of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> as was <hi>Hen.</hi> III. who conſented to the cruel Maſſaker of St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> and who ſaid one day, <hi>That if he had but one Faggot in the world, he would give it with all his Heart to burn the laſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, and ſet fire to it himſelf?</hi> Or a <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. who had abjur'd his Religion to become Roman Catholick? Such a way of Proceeding, ought it not to have ſecur'd him from all Attempts of the <hi>Jeſuites?</hi> What could they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted more from him?</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That 'twas not any Principle of Religion, as to the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40768:50"/> Perſons of the Princes, which caus'd thoſe deteſtable Aſſaſſines to act as they did; for that thoſe Princes were as Zealous Catholicks as they could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: But becauſe thoſe Monarchs, more eſpecially <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. was not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to do the Proteſtants all that Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief which the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> would have had him have done. For Example, they would have had him revok'd the Edict of <hi>Nants.</hi> The King had grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 'em that Edict of Pacification, to aſſwage the Troubles that had tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyl'd <hi>France</hi> for ſo long time. Which was the Riſe of that implacable Hatred which the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> had for his Perſon, which was never ſatisfy'd till they had laid him in his Tomb, by committing the moſt cruel and enormous of Crimes.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, now far the Fury of Religion will carry Men, when they are guided by no other Principles but thoſe of Ambition and falſe Zeal. That unbridl'd Zeal is only a miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Aſſurance, that they do God good Service in deſtroying Princes, when they are not devoted to their Party and to their Intereſts.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:40768:50"/>
            <p>From the Murther of <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, we ſhall deſcend to the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate <hi>Mary Stuart,</hi> Queen of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who was alſo the Jeſuites Victim, tho' after a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. We have told yee, That the Roman Catholick Religion is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to preſerve the Sacred Perſons of Princes or Princeſſes from the Hands of Conſpirators. Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> was as Zealous for the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion, as ever any Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in the World: And it may be ſaid in a word, That She was as good a Roman Catholick, as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was a good Proteſtant; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the Zeal of the former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it ſelf even to Fury.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, the Jeſuites having ſworn her Deſtruction, they were never ſatisfy'd till they had plung'd her in thoſe Misfortunes which coſt her both her Life and her Crown at the ſame time. She had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd a Priſoner about 18 or 19 Years, in hopes that by the Death of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſhe might one
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40768:51"/> day obtain her Liberty, and ſtep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Throne. In theſe flattering Hopes ſhe ſpent her Days, and gave her ſelf up wholly to Religion and Piety, as the only Conſolation ſhe had left, to ſoften the Sorrows and Vexations of her Impriſonment.</p>
            <p>But the Jeſuites, who never ſleep when there is any extraordinary Game to be play'd, but ſacrifice to their Tyrannical Politicks, the dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Perſons in the World, to bring about their Ends; in the Year 1582, ſent into <hi>England</hi> one Father <hi>Henry Saumier,</hi> a Jeſuite, under the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of their Deputy, with private Inſtructions for the Parts he was to Act.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, he took upon him the Habit of an Officer. Nor did he leave any Stone unturn'd, to raiſe Combuſtions and Troubles in <hi>England.</hi> However, he did not think it convenient to diſcover himſelf at firſt to any but the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Lords; and in regard Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was not then ſo cloſe guarded,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40768:51"/> but that the greateſt part of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Lords might have acceſs to her Perſon, the Jeſuite <hi>Saumier</hi> had an opportunity to introduce himſelf into her Preſence; and then declar'd it to her as a Secret, That he was ſent to her from the General of their Order, to let her underſtand, that all the Catholick Princes had extrcam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern'd themſelves in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing her Liberty, as well for the Re-eſtabliſhment of the Catholick Religion in the Three Kingdoms, and for her Advancement to the Throne in the room of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi> As for what remain'd, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought her to redouble her Zeal and Piety for Religion, and that ſhe would endeavour to diſpoſe and prepare for ſo great a Deſign, all ſuch good and faithful Subjects as were able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute toward it; to the end that in ſo doing, ſhe might be ſet at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from the Slavery of her Rival; and ſecond the fervent Prayers which the whole Order made to God for the Accompliſhment of an Enterprize ſo pious and ſo holy.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:40768:52"/>
            <p>But in regard theſe Perfidious Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple never tread a ſtep without Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in their Boſoms, while the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite <hi>Saumier</hi> fed that Unfortunate Princeſs with theſe gaudy Hopes, he complotted with the Catholick Lords the Advancement of ſome Catholick Prince of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> to the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> under pretence that he being more Potent then Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> would be able to favour and ſupport their Deſigns by force of Arms, which was ſo requiſite for the carrying on their great Entor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes. Whereas, the Weakneſs of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> would be the Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all at the Beginning.</p>
            <p>That Princeſs, over credulous, gave Credit to all the Fair Promiſes of the Flattering Jeſuite, without having the leaſt ſuſpition, that ſhe had then to do with a Knave that was going to make her a Publick Sacrifice. 'Tis true, that when <hi>Saumier</hi> imparted to her the firſt Diſcoveries of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, ſhe ſhew'd at firſt ſome Reluct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ancy to engage in ſo nice and tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40768:52"/> an Affair, that would be her infallible Ruine, ſhould ſhe happen to be betray'd. Upon which, the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite told her, That if ſhe refus'd to give her conſent, that he knew ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ways to deprive both her and her Son of the Succeſſion to the Crown; adding Expreſſions injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Circumſpection and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of that Princeſs: <hi>Quod ſi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſta fuiſſet, nec illa nec filius ejus regnarent.</hi> Saying withal, That it was the laſt Order which he had from his Superiours.</p>
            <p>Let us now ſee the end of the Tragedy. The <hi>Guiſes,</hi> who were the next of kin to Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and whoſe Intereſts were united with the Intereſts of that Princeſs, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ought to have been inform'd of this whole Negotiation, knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it. The Jeſuites had ſo well order'd their Affairs to hinder the <hi>Guiſes</hi> from giving 'em any Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by reaſon that their Aim being to deceive Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and advance in her Place ſome Prince of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> as we have ſaid
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40768:53"/> already, thought it more to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to find out new work for the <hi>Guiſes</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> that they might not have leiſure to mind the Deſtiny of their Kinſwoman.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, that great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy which was lay'd ſo privately, and carry'd on ſo ſecretly by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and Artifices of the Jeſuites, was diſcover'd at length to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by ſome of the Lords her Friends, who had feign'd to be of the Conſpiracy. Thereupon Queen <hi>Mary</hi> was accus'd of Conſpiring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Life of the Reigning Queen, and Executed, and with her fell ſome of the Lords that had a ſhare in the Plot. And the Jeſuite that had drawn 'em into all that Miſchief, fled out of the Kingdom with all the Precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion imaginable, leaving all thoſe of his Party in a world of Trouble and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hen.</hi> III. of <hi>France,</hi> who was the only Perſon in whoſe Power it was to ſave this unfortunate Princeſs, ſent M. <hi>de Bellievre</hi> indeed to Queen
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40768:53"/> 
               <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> with Orders to be very importunate for the Life of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> which he was to outward Appearance, while underhand (for Reaſons of State, and in purſuance of the King's private Orders) he perſuaded the Queen to cut off her Head, as the Common Enemy of their Perſons and Kingdoms, the Crime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſufficiently prov'd.</p>
            <p>The Diſſimulation of <hi>Hen.</hi> III. in this Affair, was grounded upon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Reaſons, which concern'd his Perſon, and the Tranquility of his Kingdom. For that <hi>Mary</hi> being the next Heir to the Crown <hi>England,</hi> ſhould ſhe have hapned to ſucceed Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the <hi>Guiſes,</hi> who were irreconcilable Enemies to <hi>Hen.</hi> III. and Counſellors of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> their Kinſwoman, would have fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd that Princeſſes Party againſt him, if they did not make uſe of all the Power of <hi>England,</hi> to engage him in a fatal War; for the <hi>Guiſes</hi> were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready too powerful in <hi>France.</hi> So that good Policy-requir'd that Prince to take all the Precautions imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40768:54"/> for keeping fair with Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> and preſerving her Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>However it were, the Jeſuites were ſtill the firſt Inſtruments of the death of that Princeſs, while they ſacrific'd her Life, in hopes of raiſing a Foreign Prince to the Throne. But what is there which they have not now done, to raiſe K. <hi>James</hi> to the Throne? Did they not find a way to ſacrince King <hi>Charles,</hi> his Brother, and to cut him off by Poyſon? What is there which they leave unacted againſt King <hi>WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM?</hi> How many Attempts, how many Conſpiracies and reiterated Plots againſt the Sacred Perſon of this Illuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Prince? And all to raiſe to the Crown of <hi>England</hi> a Furious Bigot, full of Tranſport, and in a word, a ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prieſt, more Jeſuite then King.</p>
            <p>The moſt Chriſtian King is very ill advis'd, to ſeek the having a ſhare in an Action ſo treacherous and ſo odious, as that of complotting with the Jeſuites and K. <hi>James,</hi> the Death of a Prince who now Reigns with ſo much Glory,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40768:54"/> the meaneſt of whoſe Actions will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, or at leaſt ecclipſe whatever was perform'd of moſt remarkable &amp; famous under the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great. Witneſs the Parallel that might be made between their Lives and their Actions, between which without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, there would be a vaſt Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, were they to be diſplay'd to the World without Paſſion or Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. But let us purſue theſe Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Kings, to the end we may ſhew to what exceſs of Rage and Fury the Diabolical Art and Infernal Doctrine which they have taught in the world, is able to Tranſport 'em.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1605. which had like to have prov'd fatal to all <hi>England,</hi> by the Deſtruction of the Prince, and all the Nobility of the Kingdom at the ſame time. A Blow ſo much the more deadly and terrible, becauſe it was not lookt for, nor ſo much as dreamt of, in the midſt of that Peace which <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> then enjoy'd. Nevertheleſs, the Misfortunes threaten'd by that dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Conſpiracy, vaniſh'd by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of it; ſo that it was not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40768:55"/> with any Cataſtrophe, unleſs it were, what turn'd to the Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Actors, who were to have play'd that Bloody Tragedy.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not inſiſt upon the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this Infernal Plot, as being ſo well known to all the People of <hi>England.</hi> It may be only ſaid, That this was one of the Jeſuites Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces, to have blown up not only the Soveraign Monarch himſelf, (for a ſingle Blow would not then ſerve their Turn,) but all the Royal Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and all the Nobility of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. The Quinteſſence of Jeſuitical Machination, which ſtruck with Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror not only the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy, but fill'd with Conſternation and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the Fact all the Foreign Courts of <hi>Europe.</hi> Inſomuch that the Jeſuite <hi>Baldwin</hi> being accus'd by his Accomplices, to have been one of the Principal Contrivers of that dreadful Conſpiracy, and afterwards apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Frankendale</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> was from thence carry'd to <hi>Heydelberg,</hi> and thence by Order of the Elector <hi>Palatin,</hi> ſent with his Hands and Feet bound in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:40768:55"/>
            <p>The King was alſo ſo ſenſible of his Eſcape, that he made a Speech to the Parliament upon the importance of the Diſcovery; wherein he ſet forth the great Danger from which God had preſerv'd his Sacred Perſon, the Queen his Wife, his Children, and laſtly, all the Nobility of the Kingdom, whoſe Blood was to have been all intermingl'd and blended toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a moment.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <p>What then remains, my Lords and Gentlemen, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> but that we imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the great Captain <hi>Scipio,</hi> who find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf accus'd by the Tribunes of the People, for having laid out the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Treaſure in a War againſt the <hi>Carthaginians.</hi> This is a Matter of nothing, <hi>ſaid he;</hi> content your ſelves that I have won the Victory, and let us all aſcend the Capitol, to return Thanks to the Gods for it. Let us do the ſame, my Lords and Gentlemen; Let us not give way to a <hi>Pagan;</hi> but let us return Thanks to God, whoſe mercy ſhines over all his Works.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:40768:56"/>
            <p>In like manner, does King <hi>William</hi> exhort all his good and faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, who are intereſted in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Sacred Perſon, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Thanks to Heaven, for having deliver'd him from ſo imminent a Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But what wonders of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence do we not behold in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of a Deſign ſo deeply laid for for the Deſtruction of this great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch! Without contradiction, the moſt execrable and cruel Conſpiracy that ever was.</p>
            <p>For the Relation that we have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of all the Attempts which the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites have been all along contriving and making upon the Sacred Perſons of Princes, we find not any one that was carry'd on with more Contrivance and Artifice. All the cunning Wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, all the Infernal Subtilty of the Jeſuites, ſupported by all the Power of the moſt Chriſtian King, were made uſe of in the carrying it on; and the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it was to have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd with all the Cruelty of King <hi>James,</hi> ſo that if God by Secrets of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:40768:56"/> Providence unknown to Men, had not ſtir'd up the Conſpirators to diſcover it of themſelves, the Blow had been infallible.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, the moſt Chriſtian King deſirous to hoodwink the Eyes of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and to make the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes believe, that he had no ſhare in ſo treacherous and odious an Action, caus'd a Report to be ſpread abroad of a pretended <hi>Manifoſto,</hi> which he reſolv'd to publiſh to the World. And M. <hi>Pontchartrain</hi> has already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Orders to the <hi>Gazetteer</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> to give us ſome Preliminaries in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to it, and by way of Explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what we are farther to expect, to exclaim in the Publick News a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Bloody Injury done this Great Monarch, by thoſe that charge him with being an Accomplice in ſo foul and deteſtable an Attempt. And to prepare the Minds of People to give his Apology a kind Reception, he has begun to ſay ſomething of it in his laſt <hi>Ordinary,</hi> in the following Terms, as we have here ſet 'em down word for word.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:40768:57"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="ordinance">
               <body>
                  <p>The ſame Day, <hi>ſays he,</hi> an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer diſpatch'd away by the Duke of <hi>Wirtemberg</hi> was ſent to give Advice, that a great number of the <hi>French</hi> Troops were drawn together about <hi>Callis,</hi> with ſeveral Tranſport Ships, and the King of Great <hi>Britain</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing K. <hi>James</hi>) was expected there: that being afraid that all this was done, with a Deſign to attempt a Deſcent, the Duke of of <hi>Wirtemberg</hi> advanc'd with ſome Troops to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark upon the firſt Orders of the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> This advice caus'd a great Conſternation (obſerve I beſeech ye that which follows,) and preſently, to prepoſſeſs the Publick by Artifices, like to thoſe that have been ſo frequently been made uſe of, a Report was preſently ſpread abroad of a Diſcovery of a Conſpiracy againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>'Tis not the <hi>Gazetteer</hi> that ſpeaks this, but the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> themſelves. It muſt be thought that either the moſt Chriſtian King and his Miniſters have forget the uſe of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:40768:57"/> their Sences, or elſe that they will not allow the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> to have common Reaſon, while they talk at this rate. They would make the World believe, that this is but a a Viſion; that the Conſpiracy that makes ſo loud a Noiſe, was only a Trick of State, to try the Fidelity of the People, or a Fancy of Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to blacken <hi>France</hi> with Eternal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy.</p>
            <p>If we would be ſo eaſie as to believe the Court of <hi>France,</hi> all the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racys which have hitherto been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd againſt the Perſon of the King of <hi>England,</hi> have only been pretences to gain ſome end or other; either to get Money from his Parliament, or to put a value upon himſelf, or to try the Fidelity of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>But thoſe People who advanc't ſuch Calumnies as theſe, muſt be as great Deluders, and as knaviſh in their Evaſions as the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> themſelves. By this means the moſt Chriſtian King their Maſter, in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the Maxims of the Jeſuites
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40768:58"/> his Counſellors, ſhall be always at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting the Deſtruction of a Prince, by delivering him into the hands of Traytors and Aſſaſſines; and when they miſs their Blow, and that the Conſpiracies are diſcover'd, he ſhall have a delicate excuſe to ſay, they were all Pretences or Tricks of Policy which the Prince made uſe of to advance his Affairs, and fix himſelf in the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>This is not the firſt time that <hi>France</hi> has made her ſelf known in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. The moſt Chriſtian King is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo famous in all the Courts of the Chriſtian Princes, by his Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that without doing him any wrong, we may ſafely judge him guilty of having dipt his hands in this, and to have been one of the principal Authors, as indeed he was. And without Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, we may ſafely ſay, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ingenious Tour they give to ſo baſe an Act, all Chriſtendom is ſo well convinc'd of the truth of it, that I will never believe that Monarch will ever be able to waſh it off, with all the Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence that ever he can hire to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:40768:58"/>
            <p>
               <hi>To prepoſſeſs,</hi> they ſay, <hi>the Publick, by Artifices like thoſe that have ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently been made uſe of.</hi> Obſerve here, that the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> (for they are the Perſons that ſend to the Gazet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer what the Court thinks proper to publiſh) acknowledge themſelves, that this is not the firſt time that <hi>France</hi> has attempted the of Perſon K. <hi>William. So frequently made uſe of,</hi> ſay they. Upon what occaſion? Why, upon frequent Conſpiracies; for nothing elſe can be gather'd from the Words. So then, if the Pretences were <hi>frequent,</hi> it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that the Conſpiracies were <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent;</hi> and if frequent, then real, and not imaginary; otherwiſe there had been no ground for Pretences; for the People are not frequently to be deluded by the ſelf-ſame Artifices. On the other ſide, if the Conſpiracies were real, then they could be no Pretences, but juſt Occaſions of Complaint. 'Twere well for the moſt Chriſtian King and King <hi>James,</hi> that they could acquit themſelves at the cheap rate of <hi>Frequent Pretences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince King <hi>William</hi>'s Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> we
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40768:59"/> have ſeen no leſs then Eight different Conſpiracies. In all the Campagnes ſince the War declar'd, we have ſeen New Monſters ſpring up, which the Council of <hi>France</hi> has brought forth to deſtroy this Noble Prince. The Confeſſions of the Accomplices, the intercepted Letters, the private Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of the Aſſaſſines with the Chief Miniſters of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> their Indictments and Trials, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Executions of the Traytors, have ſufficiently juſtify'd the Truth of their Crimes. All which demonſtrates to us, that the moſt Chriſtian King and King <hi>James,</hi> were the principal Authors of all thoſe bloody Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances.</p>
            <p>But by this we may ſee, how far Effronterie will carry theſe Miniſters, who will preſume to deny a matter of Fact that is apparent to the Eyes of all Men, and which all the Earth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges for ſuch. Thus, ſays the <hi>Paris Gazetteer,</hi> or rather the Eccho of the Court of <hi>France</hi>'s Voice, <hi>The Pretence of a Conſpiracy has ſerv'd to countenance the inſerting into a Publick Act, a Part of an Oath which was rejected when the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40768:59"/> Buſineſs of the Commiſſioners of Trade was examin'd; though they durſt not, out of a Remainder of Reſpect for the Truth, and the Fundamental Laws of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, make uſe of the principal Clauſes which caus'd it to be rejected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Oath which all the Lords una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly took to defend King <hi>William</hi> and his Government, againſt all the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of his Enemies; the Act of Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, whereby all the Members ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige themſelves to revenge his Death upon the Aſſaſſines, in caſe he ſhould come to a violent End; the Bill by which the Parliament is to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd, tho' it ſhould pleaſe God to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the Kingdom by the ſudden Death of the King; and the Clauſe inſerted againſt ſuſpected Perſons, by which it is made lawful for the King to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all ſuſpected Perſons, detain 'em in Priſon, and ſeize their Horſes and Arms. All theſe things the Court of <hi>France</hi> looks upon with an evil eye. Theſe are new Degrees of Grandour, Puiſſance, and Authority, which they never lookt for. This encreaſe of Union and good Correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Majeſty and his Parliament;
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40768:60"/> the earneſt Applications and ſincere Zeal of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility, by which they all unanimouſly concurr to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice their Eſtates and Lives, for the Preſervation of his <hi>Britannick</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty: All this, I ſay, extreamly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexes the moſt Chriſtian King; and this is that which makes his Miniſters give out, <hi>That the Pretence of a Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy has given the</hi> Engliſh <hi>an Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to inſert into a Publick Act, a Part of an Oath which had been rejected,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To anſwer therefore, in a word, to all theſe Evaſions, I will ſay, That the Experience of Things paſt, has ſo well taught the Chriſtian Princes to underſtand the Spirit and Cenius of the Council of <hi>France,</hi> that all the Craft and Artifice of her Miniſters will ne'er be able to diſengage 'em out of the Labyrinth into which they have run themſelves. 'Tis a Perſonal Stain that Sullies the Crown of the moſt Chriſtian King, and which will heap Infamy upon Him, as long as He lives.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:40768:60"/>
            <p>As for King <hi>James,</hi> he is a Prince abandon'd to his Sanguinary Paſſions, to Murders, Violences, and from his tender Years has breath'd nothing but Hatred and Fury againſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces,</hi> and their Governours. King <hi>William</hi> being then but Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> has had the cruel Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of it to this very day: And the Name of the Duke of <hi>York</hi> has always been ſo ſuſpected to that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, that She has always lookt upon Him as her greateſt Enemy: Witneſs the Pains he took in the Time of King <hi>Charles</hi> his Brother, to exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Him to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Wars, and to foment in Him an irreconcileable Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt this State, by creating perpetual Quarrels between the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders,</hi> upon the account of Trade; and by exciting King <hi>Charles</hi> to unite with <hi>France,</hi> for the Deſtruction of this Republick, and by uſing a thouſand other Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which have render'd him odious, and caus'd him to this day to be lookt upon as a Prince that never gave any other then baſe and mean Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of a tranſported Bigot, more Jeſuite then Prince.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:40768:61"/>
            <p>I cannot for bear reciting here one Paſſage in Hiſtory, which is in the Annals of the Republick of <hi>Holland;</hi> by which the world may judge of the Inclinations of this Prince, which always incens'd him to do all the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief that lay in his Power to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick of <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the beginning of the Year 1673 a deteſtable Enterprize was diſcover'd at <hi>Amſterdam;</hi> the Deſign of which was, to have burnt all the States Men of War. The Perſon that was to have put this fatal Deſign in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was one <hi>John Fraſer,</hi> a <hi>Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> The Duke of <hi>York,</hi> who had been all along an irreconcileable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd him by great Promiſes to go through with this treacherous Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, as the confeſs'd himſelf, when he was apprenended without being put to the Rack. This miſerable Wretch was broken upon the Wheel, and his Body expos'd upon the Wheel, near <hi>Vootewyk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is but only ſingle a sketch of his Fury: The whole Life of this
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40768:61"/> Prince has been a continu'd Series of Attempts, Treacheries, Conſpiracies, and Murders, with which the Weſt of <hi>England</hi> rings to this day. The ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary Paſſion which he learnt from the Jeſuites, who bred him form his Youth, have exaſperated him not only to do miſchief to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> but all the Proteſtant Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> without ſparing his Friends, his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, and even his neareſt Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; witneſs the precipitated End of <hi>Charles</hi> II. his Brother; meerly out of a Deſire of Reign.</p>
            <p>For Princes who only conſult their Prevailing Paſſion, and ardent Thirſt of Soveraignty, will ſacrifice all to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their End. Thus if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Great Archbiſhop of <hi>France, Marie de Medicis,</hi> Second Wife to <hi>Henry</hi> IV. concerted the Death of her Husband with the Jeſuits and <hi>Ravillac,</hi> out of impetuous Thirſt after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency. And when ſhe was confirm'd, ſhe quickly ſhew'd what Princes or Princeſſes are capable of doing, that are over-rul'd by that curſed Paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catharine de Medicis</hi> was poſſeſs'd with that inſatiable Paſſion all the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:40768:62"/> whole courſe of her Life; witneſs what we are going to recite, though ſo much care was taken to conceal it. She was, as they well know that are vers'd in the Hiſtory of <hi>France,</hi> the Mother of Three Kings; <hi>Francis</hi> II. <hi>Charles</hi> IX. and <hi>Henry</hi> II. and might have been of a Fourth, had the Duke of <hi>Alenſon,</hi> her youngeſt Son, liv'd. <hi>Francis</hi> II. being dead, <hi>Catharine de Medicis</hi> obtain'd the Regency during the Minority of <hi>Charles</hi> IX. her Son, by means of thoſe Artifices which ſhe made uſe of: Nevertheleſs, the Civil Wars over whelm'd her with Buſineſs, with Vexation, and perpetual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet, and reduc'd her even to the point of ſeeing her ſelf conſtrain'd to quit the Management of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> gave her ſoon to apprehend, that a Crown was a Burthen too heavy for a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            <p>In the midſt of theſe Perplexities, ſhe retir'd to her Cloſet, that ſhe might wholly abandon her ſelf to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude for ſome days, giving order that no Perſon ſhould come near her. But at length ſhe ſent for M. <hi>de Meſme,</hi>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:40768:62"/> a Perſon of the Long Role, for whom ſhe had a particular Eſteem, as being one that had given her ſeveral ſignal Proofs of his extraordinary Zeal for her Service upon ſeveral Occaſions.</p>
            <p>To this Perſon the Queen deliver'd a Steel Box, well lockt, with a Key; telling him at the ſame time, that the Civil War affording her but ill Preſages of her Deſtiny, ſhe thought it convenient to entruſt in his keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Sacred <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> which was the richeſt Treaſure ſhe had in the World, with Orders never to open it, or deliver it to any Perſon, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by her Command ſign'd with her own Hand.</p>
            <p>Now the Queen dying without ever ſending for the Boy from M. <hi>de Meſme,</hi> and he alſo deceaſing not long after <hi>Catherine de Medicis,</hi> the Heirs of <hi>de Meſme,</hi> kept it a long time in their Family without opening it: But at length, Time, which cauſes us to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all things, had bury'd the Queen's Commands in Oblivion, inſomuch that Curioſity would needs entice the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children of <hi>de Meſme</hi> to open the Box,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:40768:63"/> in hopes to find ſome ineſtimable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: But inſtead of that, the Box being open'd, they met with a Sight which ſtruck them with Horrour: It was an Oval Copper Medal, in form of a Buckler, which the ancient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> conſecrated to their falſe Gods.</p>
            <p>The Sculpture of the Medal repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented <hi>Catharine de Medicis</hi> upon her Knees, making an Offering to the Devil, who was painted ſitting upon a high-rais'd Throne, with all the deformed Delineations of Affright and Terror imaginable: On each ſide of the Queen were her Three Sons, <hi>Charles, Henry,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Alenſon,</hi> with this Impreſs in <hi>French: Soit, pourven que je regne. Let it be ſo, provided I may Reign.</hi> Which Medal is ſtill to be ſeen in the Family of <hi>de Meſme,</hi> from which the Count <hi>d'Avaux,</hi> formerly Ambaſſador in <hi>Holland</hi> is deſcended. And they whoſe Curiouſity leads 'em to be more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly inform'd of the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Secret, may hear it from the Lips of that Miniſter.</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:40768:63"/>
            <p>Such are the Crimes which Princes are carry'd to commit, by their exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant Ambition of Rule, or rather by their unbridled Fury and Zeal. Whence we conclude, that 'tis no wonder if King <hi>James,</hi> who has all along been animated with this Fury, and poſſeſs'd by this unruly Paſſion, ſeeks now to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain his loſt Throne by the Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of King <hi>William.</hi> But God, who has all along taken care of this Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Prince, and guarded him from all the Snares of his Enemies, will, we truſt preſerve Him ſtill a Bleſſing to <hi>Europe,</hi> in deſpite of all their dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Enterprizes. All the Chriſtian Princes unite their Prayers to Heaven for his Happy Preſervation. And, indeed, it is the Intereſt of all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which looks upon Him as Her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer, and as the Perſon who is to ſet Her free from all the Miſchiefs that have afflicted Her for ſo many Years.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſt Serene PRINCES,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a violent Outrage, an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which ought to awake the Care and Zeal which you have ſhew'd for the Common Cauſe, ever ſince the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:40768:64"/> of the War. 'Tis that laudable Ardour which ought to engage yee to redouble your Efforts againſt the Common Enemy of your Lives, your Territories, your States, and your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. you ought all to be enliven'd with the ſame Spirit and Reſolution, to demand Reparation of your Enemies, for an Act ſo baſe and ſo abominable.</p>
            <p>Let it never be ſaid, that your wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted either Counſel or Courage to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge an Attempt form'd againſt the Life of one of your Confederates. 'Tis an Act wherein you are all equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, ſince the Intereſts are ſtill the ſame which firſt engag'd you to take Arms, and which ought ſtill to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage yee unanimouſly to concurr with our Magnanimous Prince, in ſeeking all the Brave and Noble Ways imaginable that a lawful War will permit, for the pulling down ſo mortal, ſo haughty, ſo inexorable an Enemy as <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV.</p>
            <p>Nor can we endeavour this incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Deſign with more Honour, than by redoubling our Efforts to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on the preſent War with all the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour imaginable. This is that which
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40768:64"/> the moſt Chriſtian Monarch dreads; and this is that which made him haſten, had it been poſſible, the Deſtruction of the moſt Potent and moſt Formidable of his Enemies. He ſaw the impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of vanquiſhing him by force of Arms; though he wanted neither good Generals, nor ſtout and numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; nor Fortune of his ſide; and all this back'd with Treacheries and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, laid againſt the Life of his Powerful Adverſary. All this has hitherto prov'd fruitleſs; however, he muſt vanquiſh or loſe all his ill-got Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. And this it is that enrages the moſt Chriſtian Uſurper againſt King <hi>William,</hi> and inſpires him with new Attempts. Nor do they now conceal themſelves as in the former Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; they are no longer Two or Three Aſſaſſines that now ſeek the Life of King <hi>William,</hi> but Shoals of Murderers that ſhew themſelves barefac'd, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and authoriz'd by Two Kings, who give 'em their Orders under their own Hands, and ſupply 'em with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Arms, and Horſes. What a Shame! what an abject Baſeneſs is this for Chriſtian princes! And what
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:40768:65"/> may we not expect for the future from ſuch Diſciples, who have ſo well profited in the School which teachers the Art of Aſſaſſinating Kings? 'Tis a Fact which will cover the Authors of it with Shame for ever, and ſtrike a Horrour into all Pagan Princes, who never knew among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Practice of theſe deteſtable Principles. I defie any Man to find, in any of the moſt faithful Hiſtories, the leaſt footſtep of this barbarous Fury, condemn'd by all Religions, and all good Men.</p>
            <p>'Tis now for the moſt Chriſtian King and King <hi>James,</hi> to ſay what they can for Themſelves; and we expect with impatience the <hi>Manifeſto</hi> which is promis'd us. We know there is no want of eloquent Pens in <hi>France,</hi> to varniſh over a Piece of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Importance, and give it that ſpecious <hi>Tour</hi> which it ſhall pleaſe the Court, on purpoſe to put an Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon the Publick, and cover the Horrour of this deteſtable Crime.</p>
            <p>'Tis a ſort of Coin which the moſt Chriſtian King has ſo frequently made
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:40768:65"/> uſe of upon theſe Occaſions, that there are few Courts in <hi>Europe</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it will any longer paſs for current. The Confederate Princes are prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes'd of this; and know very well what <hi>France</hi> is meditating upon this Subject: Whatever ingenious <hi>Tour</hi> ſhe gives her <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> and whatever Tricks ſhe plays to ward off the bloody Reproaches which all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom will throw upon her, and that deſervedly too, ſhe will never be able to juſtifie her ſelf, nor to make an Apology, ſuch a one was will do her Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>'Tis a hard matter to render Good and juſt, a Cauſe that is bad of it ſelf; they muſt not be weak and feeble Arguments that are employ'd upon this Occaſion. This thing now in diſpute is a matter of Fact, averr'd and atteſted by the Mouths of the Conſpirators themſelves: So many Authentick Proofs; ſo many undeniable Witneſſes which the Confederates have of ſo important a Fact are ſufficient, if not to ſtop the Mouth, yet to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the World of the Guilt of the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:40768:66"/> moſt Chriſtian King. The Tryals of the Conſpirators, the Atteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Evidence, will anſwer this <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> whenever it appears, in ſuch a manner, as will be a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Conviction of the Authors and Abettors of ſo baſe and black an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize. So that unleſs the Council of <hi>France</hi> make haſte with their <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> they may juſtly fear that the Trials in <hi>England</hi> will prevent 'em, by rendring all the Artiſices of <hi>France</hi> of no uſe to her, and by publiſhing Particulars of the whole Conſpiracy ſo eſſential, that it will be a diſſiult matter for the Miniſters of that Crown to anſwer, whatever care they take, or whatever trouble they put themſelves to.</p>
            <p>We dare advertiſe them before-hand, that whatever they advance, will only ſerve to render the matter of fact more manifeſt. However, let 'em produce their Reaſons whether good or bad. 'Tis a Priviledge which the moſt rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Juſtice allows the moſt Guilty; which is, to plead their own Cauſe, and alledge what they think moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for their Juſtification, according to the Accuſations charg'd upon 'em.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:40768:66"/>
            <p>Let us then conclude, in expectation of this <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> which without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, will be one of the moſt ſtudy'd Cabinet-Pieces that ever the Court of <hi>France</hi> ſet forth; let us then conclude, that it would have been much better for the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> that the moſt Chriſtian King had never medled in this Conſpiracy; 'tis an odious Stain that reflects upon all the Nation, and blackens it with an Infamy which many Ages to come will never wipe away. In the mean time, K. <hi>William,</hi> according to the Principles of Chriſtianity, ſincerely pardons his Enemies, and prays to God to forgive the heinouſneſs of their <hi>Crime;</hi> aſſur'd, that ſo long as he is under the Protection of Divine Providence, he ſhall never be in danger, but ſhall tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over all their vile and clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Attempts, whatever Snares they lay to raviſh away his Life.</p>
            <trailer>The END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
